<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pulpit-conceptions, popular-deceptions, or, The grand debate resumed, in the point of prayer wherein it appears that those free prayers so earnestly contended for have no advantage above the prescribed liturgie in publick administrations : being an answer to the Presbyterian papers presented to the most reverend the ls.  bishops at the Savoy upon that subject.</title>
            <author>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66900</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3347</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25192</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12924839</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12924839</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95494</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66900)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95494)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 729:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Pulpit-conceptions, popular-deceptions, or, The grand debate resumed, in the point of prayer wherein it appears that those free prayers so earnestly contended for have no advantage above the prescribed liturgie in publick administrations : being an answer to the Presbyterian papers presented to the most reverend the ls.  bishops at the Savoy upon that subject.</title>
                  <author>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 63 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Royston,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to L. Womock. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: prelim. p. [8].</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95494:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95494:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PULPIT-CONCEPTIONS, POPULAR-DECEPTIONS: OR, The Grand Debate reſumed, In the point of PRAYER Wherein it appears That thoſe <hi>Free Prayers</hi> ſo earneſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for have no advantage above the <hi>Preſcribed Liturgie</hi> in publick Adminiſtrations. Being an Anſwer to the Presbyterian Papers preſented to the moſt Reverend the Ls. Biſhops at the SAVOY upon that Subject.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Sam. 15. 22.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Behold, to obey is better then ſacrifice.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Phil. 2. 17.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Royſton</hi> at the Angel in Ivie-Lane. 1662.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:95494:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:95494:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>IT was well ſaid of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Caſe,</hi> in his Sermon before <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 38.</note> the <hi>Peers,</hi> March 25. 1646. That <hi>[if either Saints may make Opinions, or Opinions may make Saints, we ſhall quickly have more O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions then Saints in the Land.]</hi> Indeed this Land is overgrown with <hi>wild</hi> Opinions, and <hi>thoſe</hi> Opinions have been planted in it by <hi>pretended</hi> Saints.</p>
            <p>The deſign therefore of <hi>theſe</hi> Papers is, to <hi>blaſt</hi> ſome of thoſe Opinions, and to undeceive ſome of thoſe perſons, who are otherwiſe too forward to loſe as well their <hi>Souls</hi> as their <hi>Charity</hi> in their <hi>Opining.</hi> For they reſt not in the <hi>Speculation,</hi> their Opinions have an influence into their <hi>Practice,</hi> and from <hi>Opining</hi> they proceed to <hi>Judgment,</hi> and paſs their Sentence, as much to their own <hi>peril</hi> and the <hi>injury</hi> of the Church, as to the <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal</hi> of their <hi>Seduced</hi> Confidents. For (amongst other things which fall under their Cenſure) while they vilifie the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> they reproach the <hi>Church,</hi> which performs her Solemn <hi>Service</hi> by it; and while they admire their own <hi>Conceptions,</hi> as the certain <hi>Effects</hi> of Grace and <hi>Vehicles</hi> of Comfort, they deceive <hi>themſelves;</hi> and while they inſinuate their attainments of <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry</hi> to be immediate <hi>Inſpirations</hi> and the ſpecial <hi>Gift</hi> of God, they delude the <hi>people.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:95494:3"/>
            <p>And yet, whether All the Devotions of the Church in <hi>Publick Aſſemblies</hi> ſhould be reſtrain'd to <hi>Preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed</hi> Forms, is a queſtion wherein perſons of great Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Integrity ſeem to be divided; and the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian-Divines</hi> more eſpecially ſeem to lay the main ſtreſs of their <hi>Grand Debate</hi> upon this Article. For they tell us, <note n="*" place="margin">The Grand Debate, <hi>p.</hi> 48.</note> This Propoſition in queſtion, <hi>[That it is needful to the Peace of the Church that all the Churches under one Prince ſhould uſe</hi> one Form of Liturgie] containeth the reſt; And they ſay fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>[It is a matter of far greater trouble to us,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 70.</note> 
               <hi>that you</hi> (the Commiſsioners they mean) <hi>would deny us and all Miniſters the Liberty of uſing any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prayers beſides the Liturgie, then that you impoſe theſe;</hi> And again they adde, <hi>[That if once</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 90.</note> 
               <hi>it be known that you</hi> (the ſaid Commiſsioners) <hi>have a deſign to work out all Prayers (even thoſe of the Pulpit) except ſuch as you preſcribe, it will make many thouſand people, fearing God, to be averſe to that which elſe they would have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which expreſsions we may perceive they have a great fondneſs for their own Conceptions: and for my part, I profeſs ingenuouſly, I was ſo far from attempting to encounter them out of deſign or choice, that I had ſome kind of <hi>prejudice</hi> to the practice I was to plead for, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving never accuſtomed my ſelf to it. But being drawn
<pb facs="tcp:95494:3"/> into this ingagement by ſuch an invitation as I could not handſomly decline, I was concerned to weigh the point in order to my own ſatisfaction, that ſo I might be the better able to give an account thereof to others.</p>
            <p>But my purpoſe is not to run over the whole <hi>Volume</hi> of their Exceptions againſt the <hi>Liturgie;</hi> (ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption would be inexcuſable, an intruſion into that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice which is incumbent upon others by a more eſpecial obligation:) but to gratifie a particular Expectation, and by thus <hi>Skirmiſhing</hi> the Party, to diſcover that they have more <hi>Colours</hi> on their ſide then ſound <hi>Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons;</hi> and though they can make a ſhift to make a <hi>Show,</hi> and by falſe Muſters to ſeem numerous, yet that their Forces are not impregnable.</p>
            <p>But I deſire not to be miſtaken; for I do not goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to diſparage ſo excellent and divine a duty as Prayer is, or diſcourage from the frequent practice of it. I am ſatisfied that <hi>occaſional</hi> Ejaculations and Prayers of a <hi>private</hi> Conception are not unlawful; and the <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> of devout and holy Souls aſſures me, that (as they may be uſed, eſpecially in private) they are of great ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy and very beneficial. But when they are ſet up in competition with a well-digeſted Liturgie, preſcrib'd and eſtabliſh'd by Authority for publick uſe, I am at a ſtand, and cannot find reaſon enough to be their Advocate, or give them my ſuffrage upon that account.</p>
            <p>For I obſerve, that the moſt <hi>Seraphic</hi> Souls, whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:95494:4"/> 
               <hi>Converſation is in Heaven,</hi> and their Lives unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provable in all things, <hi>They</hi> are much addicted to the <hi>Publick</hi> Form, and Holy Martyrs have made uſe of it as their beſt Cordial, and died with it in their boſomes. And truly the reverence which I do moſt deſervedly bear to the example and Authority of ſo venerable a Sanctity, doth heighten my eſteem of it, and will not allow me to quit my intereſt in the <hi>Liturgie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I obſerve on the other ſide, that men of looſe Principles (as to the duty of Subjection and Obedience eſpecially) do very much dote upon their <hi>Extemporary</hi> Conceptions; and <hi>Malefactors</hi> (not of the leaſt magnitude) without any ſignification of <hi>Repentance</hi> for their Crimes, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud themſelves in this Exerciſe, and are tranſported with the ſenſe of ſuch their <hi>occaſional enlargements.</hi> And for this reaſon I cannot perſwade my ſelf to think this <hi>Pretended Gift</hi> ſuch a <hi>ſoveraign Amulet,</hi> as is able to ſecure All perſons which carry it in their <hi>head,</hi> or wear it at their <hi>tongues</hi> end.</p>
            <p>But it may be return'd upon us, That ſuch as have a good opinion of the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> and offer up their Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in it, are not very ſtrict in meaſuring their lives and actions by the <hi>Rules</hi> of it. I wiſh there were leſs of truth in this Objection: But let us conſider the nature of the thing it ſelf. For God's part, being the <hi>Ancient of daies,</hi> and knowing our thoughts <hi>long before,</hi> He can no more be taken with the <hi>Novelty</hi> then with the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:95494:4"/> of our Expreſsions. And for man, That <hi>Variety</hi> of <hi>Conceptions,</hi> (ſo earneſtly contended for) hath more of <hi>temptation</hi> and <hi>peril,</hi> but not more of real advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, then a Preſcribed <hi>Liturgie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This indeed is no fewel to feed our <hi>wanton</hi> Curioſity: but for a ſolid Vertue and Devotion. In ſubmiſsion to the uſe whereof, we exerciſe our <hi>Humility</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> our <hi>Self-denial,</hi> and the <hi>reſignation of our own Judgment;</hi> all which are duties of high account in the holy Goſpel. Whereas <hi>thoſe</hi> other are more apt to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, to be made an entertainment for <hi>Fancy,</hi> and to poiſon the heart with <hi>affectation</hi> and vain-glory. If they have any <hi>Prerogative</hi> above the <hi>common Form,</hi> I am confident, we ſhall find the <hi>influence</hi> of it no where but upon the <hi>ſenſitive nature,</hi> or <hi>lower</hi> Region of the Soul. If the <hi>Will</hi> and the <hi>Underſtanding</hi> be more <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> unto God, and better <hi>fixed</hi> upon <hi>him,</hi> by this means, ſure <hi>they</hi> are able to make proof of it; and if <hi>they</hi> can doe this, <hi>they</hi> may gain a <hi>Proſelyte</hi> to their Party. But till I find better Arguments then any <hi>they</hi> have yet produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, I ſee no <hi>uſurpation</hi> nor <hi>abſurdity</hi> nor <hi>inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience</hi> in it, if it be <hi>needful</hi> to have a more particular addreſs in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> for a <hi>ſpecial</hi> bleſsing upon that <hi>Diſpenſation,</hi> That it be <hi>preſcribed</hi> to us by our <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours.</hi> And to <hi>Their</hi> Authority and Prudence I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſubmit my ſelf, with the whole Diſcourſe that followeth upon this Argument.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:95494:5"/>
            <head>Books ſold by <hi>R. Royſton.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Calviniſt's</hi> Cabinet unlock'd, or <hi>Tilenus</hi> his Apologie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> ſet forth in the Preface to his <hi>Grotian</hi> Religion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Memoranda</hi> touching the Oath <hi>ex Officio,</hi> together with an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract of the Apologie written by Dr. <hi>Coſens;</hi> as alſo a Manuſcript of Dr. <hi>Davenant</hi>'s late Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury;</hi> by Sir <hi>Edward Lake</hi> Baronet, Chancellor of <hi>Lincoln.</hi> new. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Merit of the Old Engliſh Clergy aſſerted; and the Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the New diſcovered. new. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A brief Survey of Antiquity for the tryal of the Romiſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines aſſerted in a book intituled <hi>Scripture miſtaken,</hi> by <hi>H. Ferne</hi> late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter.</hi> new. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95494:5"/>
            <head>PULPIT-CONCEPTIONS, POPULAR DECEPTIONS: OR, The Grand Debate reſumed, In the point of PRAYER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT the jealous or unwary Reader may find no temptation to miſtake our mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, we muſt premiſe, That the <hi>private Devotions</hi> of ſingle perſons are not the Subject of this Debate; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Whether the uſe of a <hi>Set Form,</hi> or his own <hi>occaſional free</hi> Conceptions be moſt beneficial, is left to every mans own experience to determine, being profeſſedly no part of our Inquiry. What is fitteſt for the Celebration of Divine Service in <hi>Publick Aſſemblies,</hi> What moſt advantageous to God's <hi>Glory</hi> and the peoples <hi>Edification;</hi> This is it which falls under our preſent Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Liberty</hi> which ſome men plead for, in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, hath been a Liberty to vent their <hi>Paſsions,</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate their <hi>Jealouſies,</hi> to diſſeminate their pernicious
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95494:6"/> 
               <hi>Principles,</hi> to foment a <hi>Faction,</hi> is ſo evident, that he muſt have been ſomewhat more then aſleep in the time of our late Storm, who hath not obſerved it. The door was no ſooner opened for the <hi>inlargement</hi> of (that which <hi>They</hi> call) the Spirit of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Supplication,</hi> but we found preſently that the Spirit of <hi>Contradiction</hi> and <hi>Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> was let looſe upon us. Whether that Spirit of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration</hi> ſo much pretended to, be a ſufficient Curb to reſtrain the like Enormities at preſent, they are beſt able to judge, who have moſt opportunity to frequent thoſe Publick Exerciſes wherein ſuch a Liberty is ſtill uſed.</p>
            <p>That the indiſcretion or intemperance of ſome men ſhould occaſion a Law that binds up the Liberty of all the reſt, may ſeem ſevere, yet is not, for thus it muſt be in the Government of <hi>Societies,</hi> not only for <hi>Uniformity,</hi> (which makes them ſolid and beautiful) but to prevent ſundry miſchiefs which otherwiſe would certainly inſue. A diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination in this Caſe would prove a matter of envy to ſome, of diſcouragement to others, an entertaiment to the itching eare, the curioſity and vanity in moſt; and he had need be mortified into a profound humility, that does not abuſe his Licence, and make it an opportunity to exerciſe his Pride and Oſtentation, in ſtead of his pretended Gifts.</p>
            <p>To prevent which Irregularities, it well becomes the Care and Prudence of our Governours, to tie us up ſtrictly to the uſe of Preſcribed Forms in our Publick Worſhip: provided thoſe <hi>impoſed</hi> be not <hi>unlawful</hi> or <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expedient;</hi> which is the main Matter of this Debate.</p>
            <p>That in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi>'s days, not only Prayers, but Pſalms alſo, were made by ſome perſons upon the Sudden and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Suggeſtion of the Spirit, is the intimation of that Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 14, 26. <q rend="inline">Leſt men through their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide</hi> Chryſoſt. <hi>&amp;</hi> Theophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lact. <hi>ad locum.</hi>
                  </note> ſhould petition for things impertinent and unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95494:6"/> that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that <hi>Gift</hi> of Prayer, was confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon ſome one that then lived amongſt them, and what conduced to the common welfare of all, that he begg'd on their behalf, and taught others alſo to peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for it.</q> Thus <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>homil.</hi> 14.</note> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> and <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad Rom.</hi> 8. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Theophylact.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>This</hi> with other <hi>Miraculous</hi> Gifts (which were needful at the Founding of the Chriſtian Church, as Scaffolds are for the Erecting of a Building) when the Church was well eſtabliſhed, were taken away, and the Fabrick left to ſtand upon the ſtrength of thoſe Pillars and Principles which were deſigned to ſupport it. And foraſmuch as the neceſſity of Prayer was to continue, the uſe of it likewiſe was to be perpetuated to the worlds end; and to this purpoſe the abſence of that Gift was ſupplied by the Miniſtery of a <hi>Liturgie,</hi> which is the importance of thoſe words which follow there in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad Rom. homil.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Of which</hi> [extraordinary diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on] <hi>the Deacon is now the Symbol</hi> and repreſentative, <hi>in his offering up of prayers for the People;</hi> which certainly the <hi>Deacon</hi> in S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>'s time performed by an eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Liturgie. <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> 1 <hi>ad Tim.</hi>
               </note> Whereupon the Father ſaith, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The <note place="margin">2. <hi>Homil.</hi> 6.</note> Faithful knew very well what they were to Pray for, all Prayer being Common (and ſo, well known) amongſt them. And <hi>Ignatius,</hi> Contemporary with the Apoſtles, and a Diſciple to one of them, and therefore well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with their mind, doth vehemently exhort the <hi>Magne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> to the uſe of one <hi>Common prayer,</hi> as we ſhall have occaſion to ſhew more fully anon. And that the Apoſtle himſelf was no enemy to this kind of <hi>Uniformity,</hi> may be reaſonably evinced from his woing the ſeveral Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in a <hi>Dialect</hi> that can hardly be forced to a <hi>Contrary</hi> interpretation; <hi>[Now I beſeech you brethren,</hi> (ſaith he, to <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 10.</note>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:95494:7"/> the <hi>Corinthians,) by the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame thing, and that there be no Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions or Schiſms amongſt you: but that ye be perfectly joyned together in the ſame mind and in the ſame judgement.]</hi> Therefore, ſaith <hi>Deodati,</hi> He requireth <hi>a Conſent in words,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">ad locum.</note> 
               <hi>thoughts, affection, and will;</hi> to the end <hi>that all may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire.</hi> To this purpoſe alſo that great Apoſtle prayes unto God, on behalf of the Church planted among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>[Now the God of patience grant you</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15. 5.</note> 
               <hi>to be like-minded one towards another, after the example of Jeſus Chriſt.]</hi> But would the Apoſtle have a conſent of mind onely, and no conſent in their expreſſions of it? an <hi>Unity</hi> in <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and no <hi>Uniformity</hi> in the holy Offices of Religion? No ſurely, He would have them accord in mind, that they might the better communicate in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of external Forms of Worſhip; for what elſe can be implyed by his following words, <hi>[That ye may with one</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Verſe 6.</note> 
               <hi>mind and one mouth glorifie God, even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt?]</hi> From which Scriptures 'tis obvious to collect, that a <hi>harmony</hi> of Devotions (as to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal <hi>mode</hi> and vocal expreſſion) as well as of Judgment, is very acceptable to God, and very commendable in God's Worſhip and ſervice. To deny this is to impeach the wiſdome of the great Apoſtle, which was aſſiſted by Divine inſpiration.</p>
            <p>Our proof then for the Lawfulneſs of a Preſcribed <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie</hi> is managed thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Service of God which is Conſonant to Holy Scripture is Lawful.</hi> [This Propoſition cannot be denied unleſſe ſomething Conſonant to Scripture be unlawful.] This therefore being granted, I aſſume,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Service of God performed by a Preſcribed Liturgie is Conſonant to Holy Scripture.</hi> Ergo.</p>
            <p>This Propoſition is proved after this manner; <hi>That Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:95494:7"/> 
               <hi>of God whereby we declare that we are perfectly joyned together</hi> in the ſame mind and in the ſame judgement, <hi>whereby we do all ſpeak</hi> the ſame thing, and with one mind and one mouth glorify God, <hi>That ſervice is conſonant to Holy Scripture;</hi> (for they are the very words of it?)</p>
            <p>By the Service of God performed by <hi>a Preſcribed Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie</hi> we declare, that we are perfectly joyned together <hi>in the ſame minde and in the ſame judgement, we do all ſpeak the ſame thing, and with one mind and one mouth glorifie God.</hi> Ergo.</p>
            <p>It is therefore no waies contrary to Scripture what we find declared <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>in Synodo Epaunenſi,</hi> That <hi>Ad celebrandum divina officia, ordinem, quem Metropolitani tenent, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciales obſervare debebunt.</hi> In the celebration of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Offices that Order which was obſerved in the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitical Church was to be the ſtandard and patern to which the whole Province was to conform. And ſo it was determined <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Conſecr. d.</hi> 2. <hi>C. Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutio.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in Concilio Gerundenſi,</hi> to this purpoſe, <hi>Inſtitutio Miſſarum, ſicut in Metropolitanae Eccleſia agitur, ità in Dei nomine, in omnibus provinciis tam ipſius Miſſae ordo, quàm Pſallendi vel Miniſtrandi conſuetudo ſervetur.</hi> And there is an excellent reaſon alledged for it in the <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 2.</note> 4. Council of <hi>Toledo, Poſt rectae Fidei confeſsionem, quae in Sancta Dei Eccleſia praedicatur, placuit ut omnes Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes, qui Catholicae fidei unitate complectimur, nihil ultra diverſum, aut diſſonum in Eccleſiaſticis Sacramentis aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus; nè quaelibet noſtra diverſitas apud ignotos; ſeu Carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, Schiſmatis errorem videatur oſtendere; &amp; multis extet in Scandalum varietas Eccleſiarum. Unus ergò ordo O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi atque Pſallendi à nobis per omnem Hiſpaniam atque Galliciam conſervetur; unus modus in Miſſarum ſolennita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus; unus in veſpertinis officiis; nec diverſa ſit ultra à nobis Eccleſiaſtica conſuetudo; quia unâ fide continemur &amp; regno. Hoc enim &amp;</hi> Antiqui Canones <hi>decreverunt, ut</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:95494:8"/> 
               <hi>unaquaeque provincia &amp; Pſallendi &amp; Miniſtrandi parem conſuetudinem teneat.</hi> After the confeſſion of the true Faith, which is preached in the holy Church of God, they would have all the Catholick Prieſts, which were compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in the unity of the Catholick Faith, to doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing different or diſagreeing in the celebration of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service; leſt amongſt ſtrangers, or Carnal men, their diverſity ſhould be taken for an evidence of Schiſm, and their variety become a matter of Scandal. They would have one order of Prayer &amp; Singing obſerved throughout <hi>Spain,</hi> &amp;c. one <hi>mode</hi> in the Solemnities of the Sacrement, one in the Offices for the Evening: Neither would they admit of any diverſity of uſages in the Church; becauſe they were of one Faith and one Kingdome. And this they declare to be according to the Decrees of the (then) Ancient Canons.</p>
            <p>But perhaps though a preſcribed Form of Prayer be very <hi>lawful,</hi> it may be wonderfully <hi>inexpedient,</hi> and under that notion it may be fit to explode and turn it out of the Church. What the <hi>Presbyterian Divines</hi> have delivered to this purpoſe, we are now ſtrictly to examine, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a punctual ſurvey of that <hi>harangue</hi> which they deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered at the <hi>Savoy</hi> upon that Argument.</p>
            <p>By what means this came to be uſhered in, we ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form you, by giving you notice that the ſaid Divines did propoſe, <hi>[That all the Prayers and other Materials of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Grand De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate,</hi> page 2.</note> 
               <hi>Liturgie may conſiſt of nothing doubtful or queſtioned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt pious, learned, and orthodox perſons.]</hi> And they adde further, that <hi>[To Load our Publick Forms with the Private Fancies upon which we differ, is the moſt Soveraign way to perpetuate Schiſm to the worlds end.]</hi> Here the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal</hi> Divines joyn iſſue with them, and return this Anſwer, <hi>[We heartily deſire that, according to this propoſal, great care may be taken to ſuppreſs thoſe private conceptions</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Id. p.</hi> 57.</note>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:95494:8"/> 
               <hi>of Prayer before and after Sermon, leſt private Opinions be made the matter of Prayer in publick, as hath, and will be, if private perſons take Liberty to make publick Prayers.]</hi> This is that which raiſeth the great cry, that hath awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned my attention, and engaged my pen to weigh the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral periods and accents of it.</p>
            <p>For thoſe <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Divines having declared their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire (which ſeems very reaſonable) that the <hi>haſtly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions</hi> of private perſons might ſtrike ſail to the <hi>preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Forms</hi> of <hi>ſolemn</hi> Service in the Church; The <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> as if they had been touch'd in the apple of their eye, let looſe their paſſions, and reply to them in theſe words, <hi>[The deſire of your hearts is the grief of ours:]</hi> 
               <note place="margin">ibid.</note> and to break the force of their reaſon as well as they can, they tell them further, That <hi>[The conceptions of Prayer by a publick perſon, according to a publick Rule, for a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick uſe, are not to be rejected as private Conceptions.]</hi> But how farre the perſon they plead for is a Publick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and how wide the Rule is which they chuſe to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure their Conceptions by, we ſhall have occaſion to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine hereafter. In the mean while, if their Conceptions be really for a Publick uſe, that is, for the common benefit of the Church, it is very fit they ſhould be allowed for ſuch by publick Authoritie; and till that be firſt obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, we cannot think fit to let them paſſe for currant, though they grow ſomewhat invective, and tell us <hi>[We had hoped you had deſigned no ſuch Innovation as this in the Church.]</hi> But what Complexion is that forehead of that cannot bluſh at ſo ſhameleſs an Imputation! For this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hath been throughly examined, and, upon triall, the <hi>Innovation</hi> is found to ly at <hi>their</hi> door who raiſe the <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour;</hi> as Dr <hi>Heylin</hi> hath evinced, in <hi>A Brief Diſcourſe</hi> touching this particular, to which we do refer them for their better information.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:95494:9"/>
            <p>And they have need enough of it; for this is ſo ſtrange a thing to them, that they profeſſe, in the next words, <hi>[When we have heard any ſay that it would come to this, and that you deſigned the ſuppreſsion of the free Prayers of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in the Pulpit, ſuited to the variety of Subjects and Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, we have rebuked them as uncharitable, in paſsing ſo heavy a Cenſure on you: And what would have been ſaid of us a yeare agoe, if we ſhould have ſaid that this was in your hearts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It had been well for the Church, if the <hi>Pulpit</hi> had never been ſo much advanced above the <hi>Deske</hi> in the opinion of the people. But that it was never deſigned for a place of <hi>Prayer,</hi> but of Exhortation onely, is well obſerved by D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Heylin;</hi> though it hath been the practice of the <hi>Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>A Briefe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,</hi> § 20.</note> and <hi>Malecontents</hi> in this later Age, to take <hi>Sanctuary</hi> there, as a place of freedome to vent themſelves, and to <hi>ſay</hi> and <hi>pray</hi> what they liſt. Otherwiſe they might have found <hi>variety</hi> enough, both for <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>Occaſions,</hi> in the ſeveral Services of the Church, to have entertain'd their Devotions. For herein we are taught to ask <hi>thoſe things which are requiſite and neceſſary as well for the Body as the Soul,</hi> as well for <hi>this life</hi> as for that <hi>which is to come;</hi> for <hi>the whole eſtate of Chriſts Church Militant here on Earth;</hi> for <hi>Jews, Turks, Infidels,</hi> and <hi>Hereticks:</hi> The very <hi>Litany</hi> alone is ſo Comprehenſive in this kind, that the attentive and devout Reader will ſtand in doubt which he ſhould moſt admire, whether the fullneſs of that excellent Form, or the injuſtice of your Complaint for want of ſuch a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion. And if in any particulars our <hi>Forms</hi> appear to be <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective,</hi> the Care and Prudence of our vigilant <hi>Superiours</hi> is able to ſupply them; and no doubt they will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it, upon a due and modeſt application to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: and then there will be no great need of your <hi>Free Prayers in the Pulpit.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:95494:9"/>
            <p>We cannot but thank you for your Charity &amp; candour, <hi>in rebuking thoſe as uncharitable, in paſsing ſo heavy a Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure on us:</hi> but we ſhould be more ingaged to you, if we might find thoſe good Qualities in you when we do really ſtand in need of them. However, we learn thus much by your own Confeſſion, that you are as liberal in giving your <hi>Rebukes</hi> as others are in paſſing heavy <hi>Cenſures,</hi> upon light <hi>occaſions.</hi> And yet I ſee not how you can properly call it a <hi>Cenſure,</hi> which preſuppoſeth at leaſt ſome pretended Miſdemeanour; for this was but a ſuſpicion or ſurmiſe what we would endeavour to doe for the future. And if you had ſaid <hi>a year agoe, that this was in our hearts;</hi> I know not what could have been ſaid to it, but this, that you did us the honour to imply, that the Good old Laws, (whereof this is one,) to which we have conſtantly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered, were written there alſo.</p>
            <p>This being well conſidered, we cannot eaſily give cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to your next Conjecture, That <hi>[nothing will more alienate the hearts of many holy, prudent perſons from the Common Prayer, then to perceive that it is framed and uſed as an inſtrument to ſhut out all other prayers, as the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters private Conceptions.]</hi> And yet we muſt tell you, the <hi>Common Prayer</hi> was neither framed nor uſed to that end; but being it is a <hi>Form</hi> ſo well weighed, ſo well known, ſo comprehenſive, and one that hath the ſtamp of Royal Authority to make it Currant, it is fit it ſhould be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to that due reſpect and veneration which our Firſt <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers</hi> and holy Martyrs have paid to it: and if all pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Conceptions (for whoſe introduction this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer hath been ſo long ſequeſtred and laid aſide,) be now turn'd out of the Publick Service of the Church, that it may recover its Original right and intire poſſeſſion therein, this is but a juſt retaliation; and the hearts of perſons truly holy and prudent will not be the more alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95494:10"/> but rather the more wedded to it upon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</p>
            <p>But you go on, and tell us <hi>[Such an end and deſign will make it under the notion of a Means, another thing then elſe it would be, and afford men ſuch an Argument againſt it as we deſire them not to have.]</hi> What your <hi>Notion of a Means</hi> (as 'tis here inſerted) ſignifies, and whither it would, I confeſs my ſelf unable to divine: but if it will afford any man a good Argument againſt the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> I have good reaſon to perſwade my ſelf you are deſirous enough of that advantage. Had your kindneſs to it prompted you to cut off occaſion from them that ſeek occaſion to quarrel at it, you would neither have ſtrained your Conſcience nor your Wit to furniſh them with ſuch Weapons as you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to Combate it. And yet the beſt Artillerie you arm them with are but thoſe old ruſty Cavils, which have had their Edges turn'd and their Points broken off long agoe in the like incounter. You inſinuate indeed, that the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument which we our ſelves afford is more dangerous then any of your framing; but let them or you manage it as your skill ſhall ſerve you, we are not frighted with ſuch <hi>Mormoe's.</hi> And your expreſſions are nothing elſe to our apprehenſion; for had you had any Confidence to prevail over us by this means, you would not have added your next Exception, <hi>[But we hope you ſpeak not the Publick ſenſe.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What the <hi>Publick ſenſe</hi> is, you may learn from the <hi>Canons</hi> of <hi>Ancient</hi> Councils, with the Cuſtome of the <hi>Univerſal</hi> Church, and the practice of our moſt Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and Learned <hi>Clergy</hi> ſince the <hi>Reformation;</hi> and to them we ſhall referre you.</p>
            <p>But for your ſelves, you plead thus in the next place, <hi>[As the Apoſtle deſired that all would ſpeak the ſame things, without giving them (that ever was proved) a forme of</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:95494:10"/> 
               <hi>words to ſpeak them in; ſo might we propoſe to you, That un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain Opinions be made no part of our Liturgie, without putting all their Words into their Mouths, in which their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires muſt be uttered.]</hi> You ſay well, ſo you might; but did the Apoſtle conjure all <hi>to ſpeak the ſame thing?</hi> and did he not give them a <hi>form</hi> of words to ſpeak them in? What think you of his <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 17. his <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 6? What think you of his <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Phil. 3. 16. his <hi>Rule of the New Creature,</hi> Gal. 6. 16. and his <hi>firſt principles,</hi> Hebr. 5. 12? Doth he injoyn <hi>Titus</hi> to hold faſt <hi>the faithful Word?</hi> Tit. 1. 9. and <hi>Timothy,</hi> to keep the <hi>Depoſitum?</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 20. and to hold faſt <hi>the Form of ſound words</hi> which he had been taught? 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 13. and yet deſire a thing ſo unreaſonable, ſo impoſſible, that all ſhould ſpeak <hi>the ſame thing,</hi> and give them no form of words (that ever was proved) to ſpeak them in? Was not this <hi>Form of words</hi> put into the mouths of all the <hi>Catechumeni?</hi> and were they not all baptized upon the profeſſion hereof? Can there be any thing more clear then this out of the Writings of the <hi>Ancients?</hi> And what if a <hi>Form</hi> of Prayer be put into our <hi>mouths</hi> too? Did not <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> put ſuch a one into the Mouths of <note place="margin">Luk. 11. 1. &amp;c.</note> his, and our <hi>Saviour</hi> another into the Mouths of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples? Why then, of all the men in the world, muſt you be left at Liberty, to vent your own Conceptions, as your <hi>Phantaſy</hi> ſhall ſerve to <hi>vary</hi> them, upon all <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>Occaſions?</hi> Is the Church better edified, or Almighty God better pleaſed with your devotions, when they are preſented in ſuch a new dreſs, then when they are offered up in the ſolemn Form of an old Liturgie? I am ſure (to ſay nothing of Diſobedience) Pride &amp; Vain-glory, Hypocriſie and Carnal craft may and do more eaſily take ſanctuary there then here. But if theſe cannot be proved to be the <hi>Shrines,</hi> by the making whereof you get your <hi>wealth;</hi> we
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95494:11"/> know you will have Artifice enough to proclaim them to be that <hi>Palladium</hi> which fell down from <hi>Jupiter;</hi> and if <note place="margin">Act. 19. 25, 35.</note> 
               <hi>this</hi> be once taken from you, you muſt preſently give all for loſt. This you make the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of Election, and to deny you <hi>this</hi> is to eclipſe, if not extinguiſh, the light of your Comfort. The Reprobates many times have the ſame ſpiritual irradiations, the ſame guſts and ſentiments with the Elect, inſomuch that they cannot find matter enough in themſelves for their own judgment to make the diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. How then ſhall the Faithful be able to make a true eſtimate of their own Adoption? Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſtit. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. §. 11. mihi <hi>p.</hi> 338.</note> hath reſolved the doubt, <hi>Quamvis magna ſit ſimilitudo &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitas inter Dei Electos &amp; qui fide caducâ ad tempus donan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, vigere tamen in ſolis Electis fiduciam illam, quam ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrat</hi> Paulus, <hi>ut pleno ore clament,</hi> Abba, <hi>Pater.</hi> Although there be a great reſemblance and affinity between the Elect of God and temporary believers, yet there remains in the Elect onely that affiance and <hi>truſt,</hi> (which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brates,) whereby they are able with much freedome to cry, <hi>Abba,</hi> Father. The Gift of Prayer (which is become ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate amongſt you to theſe Extemporary effuſions) puts his Adoption ſure, beyond the heſitation or Modeſty of all peradventure. But the plain truth is, as the matter is carried amongſt you, this <hi>Gift of Prayer</hi> (as you phraſe it) is made a temptation and a ſnare, an inſtrument of much more danger then ſecurity to mens Souls. For ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt wrought this conceit into the minds of men, that to be able to open his Boſome, or rather his Mouth, <hi>free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> in <hi>Confeſsion, Deprecation</hi> and <hi>Petition,</hi> is a certain ſign of <hi>Grace;</hi> and perſwading them, in the ſecond place, that that <hi>Grace</hi> is <hi>irreſiſtible</hi> and <hi>inamiſsible;</hi> the man that gets a volubility of tongue, a readineſs of expreſſion, with a competent meaſure of boldneſs and haſtineſs to utter any thing before the Lord <note n="*" place="margin">We might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, Cooke, Vane, Hugh Peters,</hi> &amp;c.</note>, is induced preſently, or rather
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95494:11"/> ſeduced, to flatter himſelf into an opinion (whatever his other practices and courſe of life be) that his ſtate is very good and <hi>irreverſible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to awaken men out of this golden Dream, that they ſleep not the ſleep of death, let us remember them of that which is recorded by <note n="*" place="margin">In Annal. Eccleſ.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham Scultetus</hi> of a notorious Arch-Heretick in <hi>Germany,</hi> whoſe name was <hi>Swenckfield.</hi> (He ſaith) He was wont, <hi>Ardentes ad Deum Preces creber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimè fundere,</hi> to powre forth frequently moſt ardent Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to Almighty God. And of blaſphemous <hi>Hacket,</hi> who was executed in the daies of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> it is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <note place="margin">See the Life and death of this <hi>Hacket,</hi> in <hi>Cambden</hi>'s Hiſtory of Q. Elizabeth <hi>Ad annum</hi> 1591.</note> by many, that he was ſo ardent in his Devotions, that he would raviſh all that heard him: and ſome were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the venome of his Opinion, being drawn into that contagion by no other engine but that very charm of his ardent Praying. <hi>Fertur hic</hi> Hacketus, (ſaith <hi>Hadrianus Saravia</hi> of him) <hi>in concipiendis</hi> extempore <hi>precibus adeò excelluiſſe, ut Dei Spiritu eum totum ardere, &amp; ab eo ipſius regi linguam, iſti duo crederent,</hi> &amp;c. That is, <hi>This</hi> Hacket <hi>is reported to have excelled ſo much in praying</hi> extempore, <hi>that thoſe two</hi> (his Diſciples) <hi>did verily believe him altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to have been inflamed by the Spirit of God, and that his tongue was governed by Him: and ſuch admirers were they of him, that as they believed there was nothing but he might obtain by his prayers from God; ſo conſequently, nothing that he deſired, but he might effect.</hi> Adde hereunto what is recorded of <hi>John Baſilides</hi> Duke of <hi>Moſcovia,</hi> that his carriage at his ſolemn Devotions, how he prayed, how he faſted, how ſevere he was towards others, as well of his Camp as of his Court, that did not at thoſe times con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form themſelves to his example, is wonderful to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated: and yet the man was an horrid Hell-Hound, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate Devil, to whom <hi>Nero, Caligula,</hi> and the fierceſt Tyrants of Ancient times compared may be thought
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95494:12"/> Saints, or Merciful men. He that deſires further ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this particular, may conſult Dr. <hi>Meric Caſaubon</hi> his Treatiſe of <hi>Enthuſiaſm,</hi> cap. 6. But we need not travail <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mihi</hi> p. 274, &amp;c. <hi>edit.</hi> 2.</note> out of the confines of our own <hi>Iſland</hi> for Examples to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie this ſad Obſervation: for who pretended more to this Gift of <hi>Extempore-prayer</hi> then our late <note n="*" place="margin">As eminent as <hi>Hacket,</hi> as well for their Treaſons, as for their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Gift of Prayer.</note> 
               <hi>Regicides?</hi> and yet I am perſwaded, at leaſt of ſome of them, that they had never ingaged ſo deep in thoſe horrid Crimes for which they do moſt juſtly ſuffer, had not the Devil taken his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to tranſport them by the help of this execrable Deluſion. Is it not then a ſignal piece of Charity, as well as Prudence, to withdraw that ſlippery plank that hath deceived ſo many mens confidence, and betrayed them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſhipwreck, that others may be led by a pious neceſſity to betake themſelves to that <note n="*" place="margin">The <hi>Liturgic</hi> of the Church.</note> bottome, which is more ſafe, becauſe more ſteady, and leſs apt to run upon the Rocks, or ſpring a leak, or founder under us, becauſe 'tis built and preſerved and managed by the ſteerage of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority?</p>
            <p>But this will uſher in another Objection, which falls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us in this language, <hi>[Your hearty deſire and the reaſon of it makes not only againſt</hi> Extemporary <hi>Prayers, but all</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, <hi>or</hi> written Forms <hi>or</hi> Liturgies, <hi>that were indited onely by one man, and have not the conſent antecedently of others.]</hi> Be they of whoſe inditing you pleaſe, if they have not paſs'd the <hi>Teſt</hi> and receiv'd the <hi>Stamp</hi> of publick Authority, we do not think it fit they ſhould be adopted into the <hi>Publick</hi> Service of the Church: for why ſhould any man be obliged (as he is in the uſe of the common Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie) to ſay <hi>Amen</hi> unto, or to joyn in offering up, thoſe Prayers, of whoſe <hi>incorruption</hi> and <hi>wholeſomeneſs</hi> he is not aſſured aforehand?</p>
            <p>But you demand of us in theſe (your next) words, <hi>[Do you think this was the courſe of the Primitive times?</hi> Baſil
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95494:12"/> 
               <hi>uſed his private conceptions at</hi> Caeſarea, <hi>and</hi> Gregory Thaumaturgus <hi>before him at</hi> Neocaeſarea, <hi>and all</hi> Paſtours <hi>in</hi> Juſtin Martyr<hi>'s and</hi> Tertullian<hi>'s days.]</hi> What all <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours,</hi> that is, all <hi>Biſhops,</hi> did in thoſe days, we have no leiſure, neither are we much concern'd, now to examine. Indeed <hi>Nicephorus</hi> tells us, <hi>Non omnes, quamvis ejuſdem</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ. Hiſtor. lib.</hi> 12. <hi>cap.</hi> 34.</note> 
               <hi>opinionis eſſent, eaſdem traditiones in Eccleſiis ſervarunt,</hi> &amp;c. All that were of the ſame opinion did not hold the ſame Traditions. And they which maintained the ſame Faith, did not obſerve the ſame Cuſtoms. And he gives a reaſon, why the firſt Miniſters of the Word left ſuch ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervances free to every ones choice, <hi>Ut quiſque non metu</hi> 
               <note place="margin">ibid.</note> 
               <hi>aut neceſsitate quapiam adductus, quod bonum eſt deligere &amp; ſequi poſſet,</hi> That every one might follow what is good out of choice, and not be led to it out of fear and neceſſity. But to fetch the ground of this <hi>diverſity</hi> from the very firſt <hi>Original,</hi> we may conſider, that where the Apoſtles planted the <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> they likewiſe eſtabliſh'd ſuch an <hi>Order,</hi> ſuch <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Forms,</hi> as they thought moſt apt to promote the Worſhip of God and the Edification of his Church. But becauſe they did not conſult aforehand about the inſtitution of theſe <hi>Rites,</hi> &amp;c. as they had done about the Faith, (which they were more chiefly concerned to plant and propagate) <hi>Evenit ut ſtatos ritus ab aliis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſos ſuae quiſque provinciae ſervandos tradiderit,</hi> hence it came to paſs that every one of them delivered to his own <hi>Province</hi> ſuch <hi>Rites</hi> to be obſerved as were <hi>different</hi> from the reſt. Which Rites, ſo diverſly eſtabliſhed by them, were out of a <hi>reverence</hi> to their <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Memory</hi> ſtill retained by their Succeſſors: for ſo <hi>Nicephorus</hi> concludes, <hi>Diſſenſiones tales in Eccleſiis invaluiſſe opinor, reverentiâ</hi> 
               <note place="margin">ibid.</note> 
               <hi>eorum qui eis ab initio praefuerunt, &amp; qui illis deinde ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſerunt. Nam ii tanquam leges quaſdam ab illis acceptas per manus poſteris tradidere: non ſatis pium, neque feren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:95494:13"/> 
               <hi>eſſe arbitrati, ſi traditiones, in quibus educati eſſent, non honorificè colerent, ſed contemptim rejicerent.</hi> The like hath <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiſt. Eccleſ. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>Sozomen</hi> before him. But there is beſides, another reaſon for the continuance of this <hi>diverſity</hi> of <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Uſages</hi> in the Churches of ſeveral Nations; becauſe the <hi>rage</hi> of <hi>Tyrants</hi> would not ſuffer the Governours of the Church to meet together to <hi>conſult,</hi> and by their <hi>common Suffrages</hi> to eſtabliſh one <hi>Form</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> for the <hi>Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>And yet what was done by <hi>Baſil,</hi> and other Biſhops in their ſeveral <hi>Dioceſes,</hi> doth not at all favour the Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of theſe <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> for whatever the <hi>Biſhops</hi> were allowed to doe, yet the ſingle <hi>Presbyters</hi> were alwaies obliged to uſe ſuch <hi>forms</hi> as were duely examined and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed for them: witneſs that ancient <hi>Canon,</hi> (which we find, though with ſome ſmall variety, in three or four <note n="*" place="margin">Juſtell. <hi>Codex Can. Eccl. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fric. Can.</hi> 103. <hi>Conc. Carthag.</hi> 3 <hi>Can.</hi> 23. <hi>&amp; Conc. Milevit. Can.</hi> 12.</note> ſeveral places) in theſe words, <hi>Placuit ut Preces vel Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones, ſeu Miſſae, quae probatae fuerint in Concilio, ſive Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fationes, ſive Commendationes, ſeu Manûs impoſitiones, ab omnibus celebrentur: Nec aliae omnino dicantur in Eccleſia, niſi quae à Prudentioribus tractatae, vel comprobatae in Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do fuerint; nè fortè aliquid contra Fidem, vel per ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, vel per minus ſtudium, ſit compoſitum.</hi> They would allow no Prayers to be uſed in the Church, but ſuch as were compiled by the moſt Prudent, or approved of in a Synod; leſt, through Ignorance or Careleſneſs, any thing ſhould be delivered contrary to the Faith. And we find that ſuch as were intruſted with <hi>Cure</hi> of Souls, were obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to give account at certain times to the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> whether the <hi>rites</hi> and <hi>ceremonies</hi> of that Church to which they were <hi>ſubject</hi> were obſerved. The words of the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Franc. Synod. Capitul. li.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> Synod are theſe; <hi>Presbyter in parochia habitans in Quadrageſima ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem &amp; ordinem Miniſterii ſui, ſive de Baptiſmo, ſive de Fide Catholica, ſive de Precibus &amp; ordine Miſſarum, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopo</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:95494:13"/> 
               <hi>reddat &amp; oſtendat.</hi> And this was a thing judged moſt reaſonable by <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>in Epiſt. ad Magneſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Ignatius,</hi> a Contemporary with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; <q rend="inline">Let there be nothing amongſt you that may divide you, (ſaith he) but be united to your Biſhop, by him be ſubject to God in Chriſt. As therefore the Lord doth nothing without the Father (for <hi>I can doe nothing</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 5. 35.</note> 
                  <hi>of my ſelf,</hi> ſaith He) ſo alſo let it be amongſt you, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prieſt or Deacon or Lay-perſon, let him doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without the Biſhop. Let nothing ſeem reaſonable to you without his judgment; for that thing (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it be) is irregular and offenſive to God. Come unanimouſly together to your devotions. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Let there be <hi>one Common Prayer,</hi> one mind, one hope, &amp;c.</q> From all which evidences it appears that the Liberty which we find uſed among the Ancients, of <hi>varying</hi> in the <hi>publick Forms</hi> or <hi>Rites</hi> of the Church, did not belong to <hi>ſingle Presbyters,</hi> but was the peculiar priviledge of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> in their ſeveral <hi>Dioceſes;</hi> and through the good <hi>Providence</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> of God, that <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> was at laſt reſtrained, and an <hi>Uniformity</hi> brought into the Church: For ſo <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>ubi ſuprà, lib.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 34. <hi>in pr.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nicephorus</hi> acknowledgeth; <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>qui antea quidem ſic variè obtinuerunt, nunc autem per Gratiam Dei cum tempore mutati, ad conſentien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem concordiam apud omnes pervenerunt.</hi> And beſides the good Providence of God concurring to this effect, 'tis very well obſerved by a very worthy perſon, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dike, <hi>The Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God at Religious Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, pag.</hi> 398.</note> that <hi>The reaſon why a Set Order in the Parts of Publick Service is now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the diſpoſition of the Guides of the Church from time to time, is the ſame for which men chuſe to live by poſitive Law rather then by the Will of their Rulers.</hi> And a little after, he ſaith, <hi>Beſides, in Eccleſiaſtical matters, by a ſet Order we attain Uniformity with other Churches, to help towards the unity of the whole; we avoid diſputes about what is moſt fitting, which in matters of this probable nature muſt</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:95494:14"/> 
               <hi>needs be endleſs; we avoid jealouſies and umbrages upon that which is not cuſtomable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now 'tis high time for ſome dutiful Sons to ſtep in and plead the Cauſe of the Fathers of the Church; and are not theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> very like to prove good Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates for them? Heare them argue: <hi>[And how injurious is it to the Publick Offficers of Chriſt, the Biſhops and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours of the Churches, to be called private men?]</hi> But you know, if you be not too haſty to conſider it, <hi>Volenti non fit injuria,</hi> there is no harm done, if they be contented with that denomination. But 'tis demanded, <hi>[Who are Publick perſons in the Church, if they be not? Every ſingle perſon is not a private perſon: elſe Kings and Judges would be ſo.]</hi> To which we anſwer, that <hi>Publick</hi> perſons are <hi>ſuch</hi> only in thoſe offices wherein they are intruſted. If <hi>Uzziah</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 26. 18.</note> comes to offer incenſe, though a <hi>King</hi> otherwiſe, yet in this action he is but as a private perſon. <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> muſt not be allowed to offer <hi>ſtrange fire</hi> upon the account of their being inveſted with a publick office. A <hi>Judge</hi> is but a private perſon in reſpect of that <hi>Caſe</hi> which is not within his Commiſſion to determine. And if the <hi>King,</hi> and ſuch as be put in <hi>Authority</hi> under him for the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> tie themſelves to the uſe of the <hi>Common</hi> eſtabliſht <hi>Form,</hi> as if they were <hi>private</hi> Perſons, others have the leſſe reaſon to complain for want of that <hi>Liberty,</hi> which for <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Uniformity</hi> ſake their <hi>Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours</hi> are pleaſed to deny themſelves.</p>
            <p>But you goe on with your demands, and aske us, <hi>[Have you not better means to ſhut out private Opinions, then the forbidding Miniſters praying in the Pulpit according to the variety of Subjects and Occaſions?]</hi> Why? what though we have other and better meanes? if that be lawfull, as we affirm it is, why may we not uſe that too? We ſee many times all the means we can uſe is little enough to that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95494:14"/> effect. And therefore, though we have the examination of perſons to be ordained, and do ſee that they be able to ſpeak ſenſe, and fit to manage their proper works with judgment and diſcretion, before we ordain them; yet find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by wofull experience, that men make advantage of this their abuſed <hi>Liberty,</hi> to inſinuate their moſt deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and pernicious Principles and Practices, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of publick Forms and Order, we cannot be ſo far wanting to our own, or the peace and ſafety of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as to neglect to ſtop this vent, that we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and keep off ſuch miſchiefs as have formerly made their paſſage by it.</p>
            <p>But you ſay, <hi>[Some Confidence may be put in a man in his proper Calling and work, to which he is admitted with ſo great care, as we hope (or deſire) you will admit them.]</hi> But ſtill you run upon miſtakes, in ſuppoſing no <hi>ſacrifice</hi> will be ſo acceptable as the <hi>Calves</hi> of your <hi>breed;</hi> when we are perſwaded, that <hi>the Lambs</hi> which are deſign'd for you from a <hi>Common</hi> fold will make a better Oblation. But if you think ſo much <hi>Confidence</hi> is to be repoſed in men, for that which is their <hi>proper work</hi> and calling, why do you not allow it in your <hi>Superiors,</hi> (whoſe proper <hi>office</hi> it is to <note place="margin">* See Hebr. 13. 17. 1 Theſ. 5. 12, 13.</note> govern you) and acquieſce in their determinations?</p>
            <p>But let us look upon your advice in your next words; <hi>[If you are neceſsitated to admit ſome few that are injudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious or unmeet, we beſeech you (not onely to reſtore the many hundred men layd by to a capacity, but) that you will not ſo diſhonour the whole Church, as to ſuppoſe all ſuch, and to uſe all as ſuch, but reſtrain thoſe that deſerve reſtraint, &amp; not all others for their ſakes.]</hi> To which we anſwer, That we have no reaſon to gratify thoſe men with a change of the Law, who have ſo long made it their deſigne, (and if their demands were granted would make that an introduction) to change the Prieſthood alſo. And we muſt ingenuouſly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95494:15"/> profeſſe, we can have no ſuch high opinion of thoſe mens worth, who have made uſe of ſuch <hi>Engines</hi> as they have done to help forward their <hi>intruſion</hi> into other mens poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions: and we know of no other that the <hi>Law</hi> hath <hi>laid aſide:</hi> and if they never were in a <hi>Capacity,</hi> or if they were, if they have <hi>put themſelves out</hi> of it, we are ſorry for it, but we cannot help it, unleſſe they will <hi>Conform</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the wholeſome <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Canons</hi> of the Church, by which we hold our ſelves bound to be Governed no leſſe then they. And there is a Canon, <hi>Ut Laici Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptores</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex Cod.</hi> 16. <hi>lib.</hi> 15. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>apud Coriol. Long. ad finem Conc. Carth.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Canonum excommunicentur, Clerici honore priven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur;</hi> That Contemners of the Canons of the Church, if they be <hi>Lay-</hi>men, they ſhall be excommunicated, if <hi>Clergy-men,</hi> (then) be deprived of that honour. And governing our ſelves by theſe Rules, we ſhall admit none to <hi>Sacred Orders</hi> (as far as it lyes in our power to diſcern them) but ſuch as are ſo well inſtructed to be <hi>reſign'd, humble</hi> and <hi>obedient,</hi> that out of a Conſcience of their Duty to thoſe whom God hath ſet over them, they will pay a due and chearfull obſervance to all publick Orders and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: and ſuch as theſe, we are ſure, will be no diſhonour to the Church, but will adorn their Sacred Office and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
            <p>But you tell us further (for you leave no ſtone unturn'd or untried that you can poſſibly lay for the pinning up of this your wall of Separation) <hi>You have a publick Rule (the Holy Scripture) for theſe men to pray by: And if any of them be intolerably guilty of weakneſs or raſhneſs or other miſcarriages, the words being ſpoken in Publick, you have witneſs enough; and ſure there is power enough in Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and Biſhops to puniſh them, and, if they prove incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible, to caſt them out.]</hi> For the <hi>Rule</hi> you ſpeak of, we confeſs 'tis <hi>infallible</hi> where 'tis rightly uſed and well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied; but in ſtead of <hi>ſquaring</hi> their practices by it, we
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95494:15"/> find many men do make it a <hi>Lesbian</hi> Rule, and <hi>bow</hi> it to an accommodation of their own <hi>vile</hi> pretenſions. Why? <hi>Swenckfield,</hi> and <hi>Hacket,</hi> and our late <hi>Regicides,</hi> and all <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> lay claim to this <hi>Rule,</hi> and all their deſigns and actions will be <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>right</hi> as long as their own <hi>hands</hi> are allowed to <hi>meaſure</hi> them. But let the hand of <hi>Authority</hi> apply the <hi>Rule</hi> (as it ought to doe) and then we diſcover their unjuſtice and perverſity. Is not this a part of your Rule, <hi>[Obedite praepoſitis, Obey them that are your</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Guides, and ſubmit your ſelves: for they watch for your ſouls, as they that muſt give an account;</hi> And, <hi>We command</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 3. 6.</note> 
               <hi>you, in the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye withdraw your ſelves from every brother that walketh diſorderly, and not after the tradition which he received of us?]</hi> Do you walk according to this <hi>Rule?</hi> 'tis evident you do not. Whereas you alleadge, that if this <hi>indulgence</hi> ſhould be <hi>abuſed,</hi> the miſcarriage would be <hi>notorious,</hi> and then upon Complaint and Conviction there wants not <hi>power</hi> to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Offender; This, we ſay, were ſomething, if the <hi>Liberty</hi> you plead for were a thing that would bring more benefit then diſadvantage to the Church of God: but the reaſon and experience of all Ages aſſures us it will not. And therefore 'tis greater <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> in Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours to take a courſe to <hi>prevent</hi> the ſin, then to give way to it, becauſe they are able to exert their <hi>power</hi> to puniſh it.</p>
            <p>But you alleadge further, <hi>[In all other Profeſsions theſe means are thought ſufficient to regulate the Profeſſors. His Majeſty thinks it enough to regulate His Judges, that He may chuſe able men and fit to be truſted in their proper work, and that they are reſponſible for all their Male-admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations, without preſcribing them formes beyond which they may not ſpeak any thing in their charge. Phyſicians being firſt tried, and reſponſible for their doings, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:95494:16"/> 
               <hi>truſted with the Lives of high and low, without tying them to give no Counſel or Medicine but by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of a Book, or determination of a Colledge.]</hi> If thoſe men had duely conſidered how much the <hi>Eternal</hi> intereſt of immortal Souls doth outweigh the <hi>temporal</hi> concerns whether of Eſtate or Life, perhaps their Modeſty would have prompted them to have omitted theſe impertinent compariſons. If the <hi>Judge</hi> commits a ſlip in his <hi>Charge,</hi> or the <hi>Phyſician</hi> be guilty of a miſtake in his <hi>Preſcriptions,</hi> here is no <hi>irreverence</hi> (in theſe Caſes) offered or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt the Divine <hi>Majeſty.</hi> And yet we ſee <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> have their <hi>Diſpenſatory,</hi> and 'tis queſtionable in ſome Caſes to neglect it; and <hi>Judges</hi> have their <hi>Formes,</hi> and the <hi>Proceſſe</hi> that is not according to <hi>them</hi> is pronounced void and of none effect.</p>
            <p>But you goe on, and tell us <hi>[Your Reaſon makes more againſt Preaching, and for onely reading Homilies; and it is ſo undeniable, as that we muſt like it the worſe, if not feare what will become of Preaching alſo. For firſt, It is known that in Preaching a man hath far greater opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and liberty to vent a falſe or private opinion then in Prayer. Secondly, It is known</hi> de eventu, <hi>that it is much more ordinary. And if you ſay that [He ſpeaks not the words of the Church, but his own, nor unto God, but man, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is leſſe matter] we anſwer, It is as conſiderable, if not much more,</hi> from whom <hi>he ſpeaks, then</hi> to whom. <hi>He ſpeaks as the</hi> Miniſter of Chriſt, <hi>and in his ſtead and name,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 19, 20. <hi>And it is as a</hi> higher, <hi>ſo a more</hi> reverend, <hi>thing to ſpeak in</hi> God's name <hi>to the people, then in the</hi> peoples name <hi>to God; and to ſpeak that which we call</hi> God's Word <hi>or</hi> Truth <hi>or</hi> Meſſage, <hi>then that which we call but our</hi> own deſire. <hi>We make God a lyar, or corrupt his word, if we ſpeak a falſhood in</hi> his <hi>name: We make but our ſelves lyars, if we ſpeak a falſhood to him in</hi> our own
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95494:16"/> 
               <hi>names. The former therefore is the</hi> more <hi>heinous and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full abuſe, and</hi> more <hi>to be avoided: Or, if but</hi> equally, <hi>it ſhewes the tendency of your Reaſon (for we will not ſay of your</hi> deſigne, <hi>as hoping you</hi> intend <hi>not to make us</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>If you had that gratitude which becomes you, you would acknowledge,</hi> Deus notus in Anglia, in Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannia mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num nomen ejus. Non ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter fecit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Ruſſians.) <hi>We do therefore, for the ſake of the poor threatned Church, beſeech you, that you will be pleaſed to</hi> Repent of theſe deſires, <hi>and not to proſecute them, conſidering,</hi> &amp;c.] Could you ſo lately have your hands imployed in tearing the Church of God in pieces? could you pave and paint her anew with the bodies and bloud of your fellow-ſubjects? &amp; are you now become Petitioners for the poor <hi>threatned</hi> Church, as you <hi>odiouſly,</hi> but wilfully, miſtake it; if the Church be <hi>threatned</hi> by us now, whoſe <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Teares</hi> and <hi>conſtant Profeſsion</hi> of her <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> (even with the perill and loſſe of eſtate and life) was it that, under God, upheld her in the time of your <hi>Apoſtaſie?</hi> A <hi>caſt</hi> of that <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Candour</hi> (which you pretended to ſhew where there was no occaſion for it) would have become you here, much better then the repetition of that <hi>perverſe inſinuation,</hi> that we have a deſigne to dethrone or ſuppreſs Preaching. And yet we muſt tell you, by the way, that <hi>Reading</hi> the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>Homilies</hi> too upon occaſion, (for you your ſelves read ſuch as are of your own making, and your <hi>Sermons</hi> are nothing elſe) is a <hi>Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall</hi> part of the <hi>Publick Service</hi> of the Church.</p>
            <p>As for your firſt Reaſon, it might have ſome weight in it, if the <hi>Common Prayer</hi> were deſigned for no other end then to keep out <hi>private and falſe Opinions.</hi> But we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider withall, that 'tis better <hi>weighed</hi> and more <hi>Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical,</hi> better <hi>known</hi> and more <hi>Solemn,</hi> and conſequently better accommodated to ſet forth God's <hi>Glory,</hi> and to adminiſter the peoples <hi>duty</hi> in the ſeveral parts of God's Worſhip; and being of a competent length for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of our <hi>publick</hi> Devotions, we would not have it ſuffer
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95494:17"/> any <hi>defalcation</hi> or <hi>diſparagement</hi> by the intercourſe of any private conceptions of whatever temper or complexion. And this is a <hi>Superſedeas</hi> as to your ſecond Reaſon.</p>
            <p>But becauſe we obſerve ſomething of miſtake in it, we muſt reflect upon it, to <hi>undeceive</hi> you or your Reader. We confeſſe 'tis a foul <hi>ſhame,</hi> and a foul <hi>fault</hi> too, and therefore a foul ſhame, to <hi>miſ-demean</hi> ones ſelf, whether in <hi>Preaching</hi> or in <hi>Prayer.</hi> But ſure to miſcarry in the <hi>laſt</hi> is the more <hi>heinous,</hi> becauſe therein the <hi>Glory</hi> of God is more <hi>immediately</hi> concerned; and therefore, He ſtyles his <hi>Houſe,</hi> not the Houſe of <hi>Preaching,</hi> but of <hi>Prayer.</hi> And as His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> whom we <hi>adore</hi> in <hi>Prayer,</hi> is greater then any <hi>Majeſty</hi> we can be imagined to addreſs our ſelves unto in <hi>Preaching;</hi> ſo the <hi>irreverence</hi> or <hi>profaneneſs</hi> is much greater in offering unto him a <hi>corrupt</hi> oblation, God himſelf hath thus reſolved it, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 8. <hi>If ye offer the blind for ſacrifice, is it not evil? and if ye offer the lame and ſick, is it not evil? Offer it now unto thy Governour: will he be pleaſed with thee, or accept thy perſon? ſaith the Lord of hoſts.</hi> If ſuch <hi>Oblations</hi> be a dishonour to a <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> to <hi>God</hi> they are a greater. Of all the duties of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion Prayer certainly is the higheſt in point of acceſs to God; and therefore to account it (as you doe) a more <hi>heinous</hi> and <hi>dreadful</hi> ſin to <hi>misbehave</hi> your ſelves in your diſcourſes unto men then in your <hi>prayers</hi> to Almighty God, is to preferre your <hi>Congregation</hi> before the <hi>God</hi> that preſides over it, and <hi>to worſhip the Creature more then the Creator, who is bleſſed for ever.</hi> And you muſt not think to ſhift off the <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> (for <hi>materially</hi> ſo it is) by ſaying the Preacher ſpeaks <hi>as Chriſts Miniſter:</hi> for Chriſt is a <hi>Prieſt</hi> as well as a <hi>Prophet;</hi> and we are <hi>in Chriſts ſtead</hi> (here on earth) in the <hi>capacity</hi> of our <hi>Prieſthood</hi> as well as in the <hi>capacity</hi> of our <hi>Prophetick</hi> (as that ſignifies the <hi>Preachers)</hi> Office; and we do no more miniſter to the peoples needs
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95494:17"/> in <hi>Chriſts name</hi> in <hi>this</hi> capacity, then we miniſter for their intereſt and advantage by his <hi>Authority</hi> in <hi>that other.</hi> For the Prieſt, as the common father of the world, ſtands at the altar, taking care of all, after the manner of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to whom he is dedicated, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylact</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> 1 <hi>ad Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>ad haec verba,</hi> Obſecro pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum omnium fieri obſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> have it.</p>
            <p>I ſhall take notice but of one miſtake more, and that is of making God a <hi>Liar.</hi> If we contradict what God hath ſaid, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John</hi> tells us, <hi>we make God a liar,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 10. but we doe not ſo, when we impoſe upon him what he ſaid not, though this likewiſe be a very high indignity, and abominable. The <hi>Preacher</hi> ſhall ſhut up this part of our diſcourſe, and he will determine the point for us, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5. 1, 2. <hi>Keep thy foot when thou goeſt to the houſe of God. Be not raſh with thy mouth, and let not thy heart be haſty to ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any thing before God: and be more ready to hear then to give the ſacrifice of fools: for they conſider not that they doe evil,</hi> nor the <hi>diſtance</hi> betwixt themſelves and his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> whom they do adore; <hi>for he is in heaven and they on earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, we hope, it doth appear that, as yet, we have no reaſon to repent us of theſe deſires. Indeed, if you can make it good, (as you pretend, in your next words,) that <hi>to avoid a leſſer evil, we bring a far greater upon the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> we ſhall have cauſe enough to <hi>repent of our deſires.</hi> But what is that greater evil? Why? even <hi>[ſuch as is like to ſtrip theſe Nations of the glory in which they have excelled the reſt of the world, even a Learned, able, holy Miniſtry, and a people ſincere, and ſerious, and underſtanding in the matters of their Salvation.]</hi> But ſtay, do all theſe glorious things flow <hi>immediately</hi> from your <hi>Liberty</hi> of venting your <hi>Conceptions of Prayer</hi> in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> ſuitable to the <hi>variety of Subjects and Occaſions?</hi> and are there none <hi>Learned, able</hi> and <hi>holy</hi> amongſt the <hi>Clergie,</hi> none <hi>ſincere, ſerious,</hi> and underſtanding amongſt the <hi>Laity,</hi> but
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95494:18"/> ſuch as are addicted to the <hi>Liberty</hi> you plead for? You muſt needs, if you have any modeſty in you, bluſh at ſuch an aſſertion. But becauſe you boaſt ſo much of your <hi>Gifts,</hi> and attribute that <hi>Glory,</hi> wherein you preſume your own <hi>Party</hi> doth <hi>excell</hi> the reſt of the world, to nothing elſe but your <hi>Inſpirations</hi> or <hi>abilities</hi> for <hi>occaſional</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, I ſhall introduce an adverſary as well to us as you, to <hi>vie</hi> with you in this kind; and having committed you to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſhall leave it to the judgment of the <hi>Reader,</hi> to pronounce ſentence and award the prize. Firſt then, <hi>that</hi> Perſon, acknowledging both that there are <hi>Inſpirations,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sancta Sophia <hi>in the Preface,</hi> §. 31.</note> and that we are obliged to correſpond unto them; and reckoning <hi>you</hi> and your <hi>Confederates</hi> among the <hi>frantick Spirits</hi> of this Age, which made <hi>pretended Inſpirations</hi> (or we may call them by your own name, <hi>(Extemporary) Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of prayers ſuitable to the variety of ſubjects and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions)</hi> the cauſe and ground of all our late Miſeries; He ſets down what courſe is to be taken to prevent ſuch miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, in theſe words: <q rend="inline">We ſhould, ſaith he, inform thoſe unhappy ſouls how to diſpoſe themſelves ſo as to be out of danger of <hi>Diabolical illuſions,</hi> and to be in a capacity of receiving <hi>Inſpirations</hi> truly Divine: As like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with what <hi>Caution</hi> and <hi>Prudence,</hi> but withall what <hi>Fidelity,</hi> they ought to comply with them. But eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially we ought to demonſtrate, and inculcate this fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental <hi>verity, That the general and moſt certain Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of Humility, Obedience, Unity and Peace, muſt never receive any prejudice by any pretended Inſpirations or Illuminations; ſince thoſe which are truly from God do eſtabliſh and encreaſe all theſe vertues: yea that the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Order, Authority, and Subordination eſtabliſhed by God in his Church (by which alone it becomes one Body, and not a monſtrous heap of unlike, unproportionable members, fighting and devouring one another) muſt be the</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:95494:18"/> 
                  <hi>Rule by which to examine and judge, to pronounce ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for or againſt all manner of Inſpirations.</hi>
               </q> Having laid down this his <hi>fundamental</hi> Rule, he proceeds a little after to compare <hi>their Inſpirations</hi> with <hi>yours,</hi> in ſeveral <note place="margin">§. 33, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> particulars. <q rend="inline"> And in the firſt place, ſaith he, <hi>here</hi> the only proper <hi>Diſpoſition</hi> towards the receiving of <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Irradiations</hi> from <hi>God's holy Spirit</hi> is an <hi>abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of life,</hi> a ſequeſtration from all buſineſſes that concern others, and an attendance to God alone in the depth of the Spirit: Whereas <hi>their Lights</hi> come never more frequently then when either being alone they yield to diſcontented unquiet <hi>paſsions</hi> and murmurings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about the behaviour and actions of others; or when in cloſe Meetings and <hi>Conſpiracies</hi> they vent ſuch paſſions by <hi>Invectives</hi> againſt the Governours of the Church or State. Secondly, The <hi>Lights here</hi> deſired and prayed for are ſuch as do expell all <hi>images of Creatures,</hi> and do calm all manner of <hi>Paſsions,</hi> to the end that the Soul be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a vacuity, may be more capable of receiving and entertaining God in the pure <hi>fund</hi> of the Spirit: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>their Lights</hi> fill them with all tumults, diſquieting Images and <hi>Phantaſms</hi> concerning the ſuppoſed miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages of all others but themſelves; and not onely heighten their <hi>Paſsions,</hi> but urge them to moſt terrible deſolating effects. Thirdly, The <hi>Prayer here acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged</hi> to be the moſt effectual <hi>Inſtrument</hi> to procure <hi>Divine Light,</hi> is a <hi>pure, recollected, intime</hi> Prayer of the Spirit: Whereas the Prayer that <hi>they</hi> glory in is onely an acquired ability and ſleight to talk earneſtly to God before others, and oft thereby to communicate their <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> and diſcontents to their Brethren. Fourthly, <hi>Here are no new Speculative Verities</hi> or <hi>Revelations of Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> pretended; no private new-found-out interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Scriptures bragg'd of: Whereas among <hi>them</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:95494:19"/> every day produces a new Fancy, which muſt gather new Company. Fifthly, <hi>Here the eſtabliſh'd Order of God's Church,</hi> and the <hi>Unity</hi> eſſential thereto is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced; yea the <hi>Inſpirations</hi> expected and obtained by <hi>pure internal Prayer</hi> do more firmly and unalterably fix ſouls under this <hi>Obedience,</hi> and to this <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Unity;</hi> inſomuch as whatſoever pretended <hi>Lights</hi> do endanger the diſſolving of <hi>Unity,</hi> or do croſs Lawful <hi>Authority,</hi> or ſhall be rejected by it, they are preſently ſuſpected and extinguiſhed: Whereas <hi>thoſe mens Lights</hi> teach them nothing ſo much as to contemn and oppoſe all <hi>external Authority,</hi> and to diſſipate <hi>Unity,</hi> diſperſing the <hi>Body of Chriſtianity</hi> into innumerable <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles.</hi> Sixthly, <hi>Our Lights</hi> teach us to attend only to God and our own Souls, and never to intereſs our ſelves in any care or imployment about others, till evidently God's <hi>Inſpirations</hi> force us, and <hi>external Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> obligeth us thereto: Whereas <hi>their Lights</hi> ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them incapable of <hi>Solitude,</hi> and thruſt them abroad to be <hi>Reformers of others,</hi> being themſelves impatient of all <hi>Reformation</hi> and <hi>Contradiction.</hi> Seventhly, <hi>Our Lights</hi> make us to fear and avoid all <hi>Supereminence</hi> and <hi>Judicature,</hi> all ſenſual pleaſures, defires of wealth, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, &amp;c. Whereas <hi>their Lights</hi> engage them violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and deeply in all theſe carnal and ſecular waies, and (for the attaining of theſe) in <hi>Tumults, Sedition, Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed</hi> and <hi>War; in a word,</hi> in all manner of actions and deſigns moſt contrary to the Spirit of Chriſtianity. Eighthly, and laſtly, <hi>Our Lights,</hi> if they ſhould chance ſometimes to be miſtaken by us, no harm at all would accrue to others, and not any conſiderable prejudice to our ſelves; becauſe, as hath been ſaid, the <hi>matters</hi> in which they direct us are in their Nature <hi>Indifferent,</hi> and are ordered onely towards a more perfect loving of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95494:19"/> God, and withdrawing us from Creatures: Whereas all the Miſeries and almoſt all the diſorders and enormous Vices of the <hi>Nation</hi> (he means <hi>England)</hi> are the effects of their <hi>misleading Lights.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline"> Thus (ſaith he) ſtands the caſe betwixt <hi>Catholick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirations</hi> and the <hi>pretended Inſpirations of Sectaries.</hi> Such is that Spirit of <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> and ſo divine are the effects of it, directing the minds of good, humble, obedient and devout Catholicks: And ſuch is the Spirit of <hi>Diſorder, Revenge, Wrath, Rebellion,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo diſmal are the effects of that <hi>Spirit</hi> wherewith ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opinionated, preſumptuous, frantick <hi>Sectaries</hi> are agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated. What reſemblance, what agreement can there be between <hi>theſe two?</hi> This <hi>evill Spirit,</hi> though it Sacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly uſurps <hi>the name,</hi> yet it doth not ſo much as counterfeit the <hi>operations</hi> of the <hi>good one:</hi> Or if with the <hi>name</hi> it doth ſometimes ſeem to counterfeit ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reſemblance, and to ſome perſons ſhew <hi>demure looks,</hi> &amp;c. yet the <hi>Aequivocation</hi> and <hi>Hypocriſy</hi> is ſo groſſe and palpable, that they muſt put out their eies that perceive it not.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus having given you an account, in his own very words, what <hi>opinion</hi> that man hath of you, I ſhall leave you to reflect upon them, and as you find your ſelves able to impugn them, to challenge him ſtill to the combate for that <hi>Glory</hi> wherein you are ſo confident <hi>you excell all the world beſides.</hi> In the mean while, we ſhall force our ſelves into ſo much patience as to read over your Arguments, <hi>(without Reaſon)</hi> why the denying you the <hi>free Liberty</hi> of venting your <hi>Conceived</hi> prayers in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> ſuitable to the <hi>variety</hi> of <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>Occaſions,</hi> ſhould ſtrip theſe Nations of an <hi>able, holy Miniſtry,</hi> as you affirm.</p>
            <p>For Firſt, (you ſay) <hi>[It is well known that an Ignorant man may read a Prayer and Homily, as diſtinctly and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dably</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:95494:20"/> 
               <hi>as a learned Divine; and ſo may doe the work of a Miniſter, if this be it.]</hi> But we ſay this is not <hi>it,</hi> though an <hi>appendant</hi> to it or an <hi>Ingredient</hi> of it; and ſo that Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment comes to nothing. And the next will amount to no more, when you adde, that <hi>[it is</hi> ſo <hi>well known that mans nature is ſo addicted to eaſe and ſenſual diverſions, as that multitudes will make no better preparations, when they find that no more is neceſſary. When they are as capable of their places and maintenance if they can but read, and are forced upon no exerciſe of their Parts, which may detect and ſhame their ignorance, but the ſame words are to be read by the ableſt and the ignoranteſt man, it is certain, that this will make multitudes idle in their</hi> Academical <hi>Studies, and multitudes to ſpend their time idly all the year in the courſe of their Miniſtry: and when they have no neceſsity, that they are ſenſible of, of diligent ſtudies, it will let looſe their fleſhly voluptuous inclinations; and they will ſpend their time in ſports and drinking and prating and idleneſs, and this will be a ſeminary of luſt: or they will follow the world, and drown themſelves in Covetouſneſs and Ambition. And their hearts will be like their ſtudies. As it is the way to have a holy, able Miniſtry, to engage them to holy ſtudies, to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on God's Law day and night; ſo it is the way to have an ignorant, prophane and ſcandalous Miniſtry (and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently enemies to ſerious Godlineſs in others) to impoſe upon them but ſuch a work as in ignorance and idleneſs they may perform as well as the judicious and the diligent.]</hi> Thus you are pleaſed to declaim (for want of Reaſon:) but how little this ſignifies to the Cauſe you have in hand, the Reader will be able to judge by our <hi>Reply,</hi> which is, in ſhort, as followeth. Firſt, That ſuch as are <hi>Expectants,</hi> muſt ſubmit themſelves to an <hi>Examination</hi> of their Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, before they can be admitted unto <hi>holy Orders;</hi> and if they have neglected their <hi>Academical</hi> ſtudies, this alone
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95494:20"/> will <hi>detect</hi> and <hi>ſhame</hi> their <hi>Ignorance:</hi> and if we finde they have been ſo bad proficients, (though they ſhould paſſe in a crowd for their <hi>Degrees,</hi> which yet we heartily wiſh may be prevented, by the care of thoſe who from time to time ſhall have the Government of the <hi>Univerſities)</hi> that they are able to doe nothing but to <hi>read,</hi> we ſhall reject them as <hi>unfit</hi> for the <hi>Prieſtly</hi> office. For, (ſecondly) we know that <hi>Reading</hi> is not all our work; <hi>Sermons</hi> are to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, <note place="margin">Where doth Learning and Devotion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound more then in ſuch Churches and among ſuch So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties as are ſtrictly tied to the uſe of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Forms?</note> and therein the <hi>Scriptures</hi> to be expounded, emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent <hi>Controverſies</hi> to be decided, <hi>Caſes</hi> of Conſcience to be reſolved, the <hi>weak</hi> to be ſupported, the <hi>doubtful</hi> ſtrengthned, the diſconſolate and <hi>languiſhing</hi> comforted, and ſuch doctrines adminiſtred as may tend to the <hi>edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of all the people: and the <hi>neglect</hi> of this their neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary duty, or their <hi>failing</hi> in it, will ſufficiently <hi>detect</hi> and <hi>ſhame</hi> mens <hi>ignorance;</hi> and the very <hi>fear</hi> of this will ingage them to be ſedulous and diligent in their ſtudies. Thirdly, As for your <hi>extemporary Conceptions</hi> of Prayer ſuitable to the <hi>variety</hi> of <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>Occaſions,</hi> they coſt you no time of <hi>premeditation</hi> in your Studies: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (fourthly) We have obſerved that many of your <hi>Gifted-men</hi> have been as much <hi>immerſed</hi> and drown'd in <hi>Luſt</hi> and <hi>Idleneſs,</hi> in <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Ambition,</hi> as any other; and if it would bring any advantage to the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Profeſsion,</hi> we could give you ſome <hi>Centuries</hi> of ſuch perſons; but, in charity, we ſhall ſpare you. Fifthly, We have a <hi>Conſcience</hi> of our <hi>duty</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>man,</hi> (we need not diſparage our ſelves in ſaying <hi>as well as you)</hi> and an eye to that great recompence of reward, deſigned to <hi>ſpur</hi> us up unto it; and how many of our perſwaſion, even upon this ſingle account, [do <hi>ſtudy to ſhew themſelves ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 15.</note> 
               <hi>unto God, work-men that need not be aſhamed, right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dividing the word of truth]</hi> we leave it to <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>world</hi> to judge. Sixthly, and laſtly, If there be any ſo
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95494:21"/> forgetful of their duty, as <hi>to let looſe their fleſhly voluptuous inclinations,</hi> and to ſpend their time in <hi>Sports,</hi> and <hi>Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Prating</hi> and <hi>Idleneſs;</hi> a thouſand to one, ſome <hi>eye of inſpection</hi> will take notice of their miſcarriages, (unleſs they be all committed in a very dark corner) and ſure (as you ſay) there is <hi>power</hi> enough in <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> to puniſh them, and if they prove <hi>incorrigible,</hi> to caſt them out.</p>
            <p>It is a ſhameleſs Calumny to affirm, (for you do more then inſinuate) that there is no <hi>other work impoſed</hi> upon <hi>Miniſters</hi> but what they may <hi>perform</hi> in <hi>ignorance and idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> as well as the <hi>judicious and the diligent.</hi> Let any man but conſider what a charge is laid upon <hi>Prieſts</hi> at their <hi>Ordination,</hi> and he muſt needs be <hi>convinced,</hi> that the Work <hi>then</hi> and <hi>there</hi> aſſigned them is enough to <hi>exerciſe</hi> all their ableſt Parts as well in the <hi>Pulpit</hi> as out of it: and therefore you might have conſulted your own credit bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, had you forborn that following exprobration, That, <hi>[in Catechizing, in private Baptiſm, and Communion, and in the Viſitation of the Sick, their work is alſo ſuch as a School-boy may doe as well as they.]</hi> To which impudent Slander we ſhall confront the <hi>Charge</hi> aforeſaid, and that will be ſufficient to confute it. Thus then the Holy Church conjures all that enter into thoſe Sacred Orders: <hi>[We exhort you in the name of our Lord</hi> Jeſus <hi>Chriſt, to have</hi> 
               <note place="margin">After the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Supremacy</hi> is adminiſtred, this <hi>Charge</hi> is given to the <hi>Prieſts</hi> to be <hi>Ordained.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in remembrance into how high a dignity, and to how charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able an Office, ye be called; that is to ſay, the Meſſengers, the Watchmen, the Paſtours and the Stewards of the Lord; to teach, to premoniſh, to feed and provide for the Lords Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, to ſeek for Chriſts ſheep that be diſperſed abroad, and for his Children which be in the midſt of this naughty world, to be ſaved through Chriſt for ever. Have alwaies therefore printed in your remembrance how great a treaſure is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to your charge: for they be the Sheep of Chriſt, which</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:95494:21"/> 
               <hi>he bought with his</hi> death, <hi>and for whom he ſhed his</hi> bloud. <hi>The Church and Congregation, whom ye muſt ſerve, is his</hi> Spouſe <hi>and his</hi> Body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And if it ſhall chance the ſame Church, or any Member thereof, to take any hurt or hinderance by reaſon of your</hi> negligence, <hi>ye know the greatneſs of the</hi> fault, <hi>and alſo of the horrible</hi> puniſhment <hi>which will enſue. Wherefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with your ſelves the end of your</hi> Miniſtery, <hi>towards the</hi> children <hi>of God, towards the</hi> Spouſe <hi>and</hi> Body <hi>of Chriſt, and ſee that you never ceaſe your labour, your care and diligence, untill you have done all that lieth in you, according to your bounden duty, to bring all ſuch as are or ſhall be committed to your Charge, unto that agreement in Faith and Knowledge of God, and to that ripeneſs and perfectneſs of age in Chriſt, that there be no place left among you either of</hi> Errour <hi>in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or for</hi> Viciouſneſs <hi>in Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then, foraſmuch as your office is both of ſo great</hi> excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency <hi>and of ſo great</hi> difficulty, <hi>ye ſee with how great care and ſtudy ye ought to apply your ſelves, as well that you may ſhew your ſelves kind to that Lord who hath placed you in ſo high a dignity, as alſo to beware that neither you your ſelves offend, neither be occaſion that others offend. Howbeit, ye cannot have a mind and a will thereto of</hi> your ſelves, <hi>for that power and ability is given of God alone. Therefore ye ſee how ye</hi> ought <hi>and have need earneſtly to</hi> pray <hi>for his</hi> holy Spirit. <hi>And ſeeing that you cannot by any other means com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs the doing of ſo weighty a work pertaining to the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man, but with</hi> doctrine <hi>and</hi> exhortation <hi>taken out of the holy</hi> Scriptures, <hi>and with</hi> a life <hi>agreeable unto the ſame; ye perceive how ſtudious ye ought to be in reading and learning the Scriptures, and in framing the</hi> manners <hi>both of</hi> your ſelves <hi>and of</hi> them <hi>that ſpecially pertain unto you, according to the Rule of the ſame Scriptures. And for this ſelf-ſame cauſe, ye ſee how ye ought to forſake and ſet</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:95494:22"/> 
               <hi>aſide (as much as you may) all</hi> worldly <hi>cares and ſtudies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we appeal to your own Conſciences, whether the Church impoſeth upon <hi>Prieſts</hi> (when ſhe <hi>ordains</hi> them to the <hi>Miniſtery)</hi> no other work then what <hi>a School-boy may doe as well as they;</hi> or but <hi>ſuch</hi> a work as in <hi>ignorance</hi> and <hi>idleneſs</hi> they may perform as well as the <hi>judicious</hi> and the <hi>diligent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you will be ſo juſt as to <hi>repair</hi> the Honour of the Church (as you are obliged,) for thus aſperſing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching her, we will grant your following aſſertions with ſome <hi>additional amendments,</hi> That <hi>[the</hi> Prieſts <hi>Miniſterial work is, to ſhew men their ſins, and to preach the wonderful Myſteries of the Goſpel, to help men to ſearch and underſtand the Scriptures, and to ſearch and know their hearts, and to know God in Chriſt,</hi> [and to be ſubject to <hi>principalities</hi> 
               <note place="margin">It ſeems, Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours makes not one of the links in your chain of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, that leads men to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
               <hi>and powers,</hi> to obey <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> as <hi>Supreme,</hi> and them that are <hi>commiſsioned</hi> under him, as his <hi>Miniſters;</hi> to render unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s, and to <hi>God</hi> the things that are <hi>God</hi>'s; to pay all due <hi>reverence</hi> and <hi>ſubmiſsion</hi> to all <hi>Governours,</hi> as well <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> as <hi>Civil,</hi> that we may lead <hi>a quiet</hi> and a peaceable life in all <hi>Godlineſs</hi> and <hi>honeſty;</hi> and upon <hi>this</hi> account] <hi>to hope for the glory that is to be revealed, and fervently to pray for the ſucceſs of his endeavours, and the bleſsing of the Goſpel on the people, and chearfully to praiſe God for his various benefits:</hi> And we confeſs <hi>this cannot be well done without abilities.]</hi> Though it becomes not a good Chriſtian to make <hi>oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of his good works, yet we acknowledge 'tis his duty ſo to make his <hi>light ſhine before men,</hi> that they may <hi>ſee it,</hi> and be <hi>edified</hi> by it, to the advancement of God's <hi>Glory.</hi> And our <hi>own</hi> judgment and experience tells us as well as you, <hi>[that God ordinarily proportioneth the ſucceſs and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the skill, diligence and holineſs of the Inſtruments; and bleſſeth not the labours of ignorant, ungodly droans, as</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:95494:22"/> 
               <hi>he doth the labours of faithful able Miniſters. And alſo that the readieſt way to bring the Goſpel into contempt in the world, and cauſe all Religion to dwindle away into</hi> Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity <hi>firſt, and then to</hi> Barbariſm <hi>and</hi> Brutiſhneſs, <hi>is to let in an</hi> ignorant, idle, vicious <hi>Miniſtry, that will become the peoples ſcorn: yea,</hi> that <hi>this is the way to extirpate</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">And will not Sedition and Rebellion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke all Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Civil Magiſtrates to root out that Religion that doth teach and patronize ſuch practices?</note> Chriſtianity <hi>out of any Countrey in the World;</hi> and 'tis a ſign <hi>it is decaying apace, when men grow ignorant of the</hi> nature <hi>and</hi> reaſons <hi>of it, and</hi> unexperienced <hi>in its power and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful</hi> fruits, <hi>and when the</hi> Teachers <hi>themſelves grow unable to defend it.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſay therefore with <hi>Gelaſius, (in Epiſt. ad Epiſcopos Lucaniae, cap.</hi> 18.) <hi>Literis carens, Sacris non poteſt aptus eſſe Myſteriis,</hi> He that wants Learning is unfit to diſpenſe the Sacred Myſteries: and as it is <hi>in Concilio Toletano</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. <hi>Ignorantia, mater cunctorum Errorum, maximè in Sacerdotibus vitanda eſt, qui docendi officium Populi ſuſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perunt,</hi> Ignorance, the Mother of all Errors, is eſpecially to be avoided in the Prieſts, whoſe Office it is to inſtruct others. Hereupon we do very readily ſubſcribe to that which we find <hi>in Concilio Romano ſub Eugenio</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Presbyteri ſint literati, aliter enim quomodo erunt Magiſtri, qui non fuerunt Diſcipuli,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Iſti ſunt canes muti non va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentes latrare,</hi> Let the Prieſts be Learned; otherwiſe how ſhall they be Teachers, who were never Diſciples, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thoſe are dumb doggs which cannot bark. We ſhall therefore beſpeak all our Brethren of the Prieſthood in the words of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Ambroſe, Dignè cognoſcamus quid ſumus;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In lib. de dignit. Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dot. cap.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; quod ſumus profeſsione, actione potius quàm nomine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtremus; nomen congruat actioni, actio reſpondeat no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini: ne ſit nomen inane, &amp; crimen immane; ne ſit ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor ſublimis, &amp; vita deformis; ne ſit deifica profeſsio, &amp; illicita actio; ne ſit gradus excelſus, &amp; deformis exceſſus; ne habeatur in Eccleſia Cathedra ſublimior, &amp; conſcientia</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:95494:23"/> 
               <hi>Sacerdotis reperiatur humilior; ne locutionem ſimulemus columbinam, &amp; mentem habeamus caninam; ne profeſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem monſtremus ovinam, &amp; ferocitatem habeamus lupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam: ne dignè nobis per Prophetam reſpondeatur à Domino, Populus hic labiis me honorat, cor autem longè eſt à me.</hi> Let us know our ſelves; and let our Practice be ſuitable to our profeſſion: that the dignity of our Office may not be blemiſhed by the iniquity of our converſation. Let us not be Wolves, nor Doggs, nor Swine in Sheeps cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; leſt that exprobration deſervedly fall upon us, [This people honour me with their lips, but their heart is far from me.]</p>
            <p>But for the honour of the Reverend <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable</hi> Clergy, we muſt take the confidence to tell the world, that <hi>they</hi> have been the <hi>Chariots</hi> of this our <hi>Iſrael</hi> and the <hi>horſemen</hi> thereof; <hi>Their</hi> Armes have been the <hi>Defence</hi> of our <hi>Religion,</hi> their <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> its <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication</hi> from time to time. And for proof of this we need refer you to no other <hi>evidence</hi> then the <hi>Obſervation</hi> and <hi>acknowledgement</hi> of that Learned <note n="*" place="margin">Deodati.</note> Miniſter of <hi>Geneva,</hi> in his Letter to the late Aſſembly. And if through the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of theſe later daies a multitude of <hi>their</hi> former Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents have been tempted to <hi>withdraw</hi> themſelves from their <hi>Communion</hi> and <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> it is no great wonder; for the Holy Ghoſt hath told us of falſe Prophets and <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 19.</note> ſeducing Spirits, and <hi>why</hi> God is pleaſed to <hi>permit</hi> them; and of an ingrateful <hi>giddy</hi> people, that would eaſily ſuffer themſelves to be <hi>ſeduced,</hi> and become guilty of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie. <hi>For the time will come, when they will not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 1.</note> 
               <hi>endure ſound doctrine, but will depart from the Faith,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>and give heed to ſeducing Spirits, and after their own luſts will heap to themſelves Teachers, having itching eares. And they will turn away their ears from the truth, and be turned unto Fables. And men ſhall be lovers of their own</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 2, &amp;c.</note>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:95494:23"/> 
               <hi>ſelves, covetous, boaſters, proud, blaſphemers, diſobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy, without naturall affection, truce breakers, falſe accuſers, incontinent, fierce, deſpiſers of thoſe that are good, Traitors, heady, high-minded, lovers of pleaſures more then lovers of God; Having a Form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, but denying the power thereof. And through Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall they, with feigned words, make merchandiſe of you: and ſhall creep into houſes, and lead captive ſilly women</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 6.</note> 
               <hi>laden with ſins, and led away with divers luſts.</hi> And of the very <hi>Clergie</hi> ſhall men <hi>ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things, to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 20. 30.</note> 
               <hi>draw Diſciples after them. And many ſhall follow their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 2.</note> 
               <hi>waies, by reaſon of whom the way of truth ſhall be evil ſpoken of.</hi> Our Saviour Chriſt himſelf, a perſon beyond all exception, both for <hi>Parts, Holineſs,</hi> and <hi>Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> finds occaſion to complain that his <hi>Miniſtry</hi> was deſerted by ſuch as were inclinable to flock after ſome <hi>new-comer,</hi> though he had no other <hi>warrant</hi> for his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking but what was drawn up by his own preſumption.</p>
            <p>But (to follow your ſteps) you adde <hi>[That whatſoever can be expected duly to affect the heart, muſt keep the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect and all the faculties awake in diligent attention and exerciſe.]</hi> It is very true, A manifold attention is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to make our ſacred <hi>office</hi> of Prayer <hi>devout</hi> and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: An attention, 1. <hi>ad verba, ut rectè proferantur;</hi> 2. <hi>ad verborum ſenſum, ut mente &amp; corde percipiatur;</hi> 3. <hi>ad Deum, quem ut praeſentem recitans (officium) intuetur, ad cumque petitiones ſuas dirigit, &amp; circa quem occupatur, veritates aut myſteria fidei conſiderando, ut ſic ſe ad ejus amorem excitet.</hi> But you ſay <hi>[in the uſe of a form, which we have frequently heard and read, the faculties are not ſo neceſsitated and urged to attention and ſerious exerciſe, as they be when from our own underſtanding we are ſet about the natural work of repreſenting to others what we diſcern and feel.]</hi> Then belike <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> and our Bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:95494:24"/> did their Diſciples a <hi>diſadvantage;</hi> they ſhould not have preſcribed <hi>formes</hi> to them, but have diſſuaded them from the <hi>uſe</hi> of all ſuch in the Exerciſe of their Devotion: which whether it be modeſt or impious to affirm, is left to the judgment of the Reader. But you ſay further, <hi>[Mans mind is naturally ſloathful, and will take its eaſe, and remit its ſeriouſneſs longer then it is urged by neceſsity, or drawn out by delight.]</hi> Why? is there not a <hi>neceſsity</hi> laid upon us? Is there not a <hi>Woe</hi> belongs to us, if we <hi>pray not,</hi> if we <hi>obey not</hi> the commands of the <hi>Holy Church</hi> preſcribing a <hi>Form</hi> of Prayer to us? If we be obliged to obey <hi>this</hi> her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, we are obliged to be <hi>ſerious</hi> in that obedience. Though ſhe cannot judge of <hi>Internal Acts,</hi> ſhe may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them; and ſhe is ſuppoſed to doe ſo, ſeeing <hi>External Acts,</hi> under her command, are not <hi>Acts of Vertue</hi> without thoſe <hi>Internal</hi> ones: Otherwiſe it were poſſible to ſatisfie the <hi>Precepts</hi> of the Church by a <hi>mere</hi> Simulation and <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie,</hi> which is abſurd. A <hi>neceſsity</hi> therefore is laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, to <hi>urge</hi> us to be <hi>ſerious</hi> in the uſe of this <hi>Form</hi> of Prayer. And if we ſet ſo high an <hi>eſtimate</hi> upon God's <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> and our own <hi>ſalvation</hi> as they deſerve, I ſee no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why this <hi>ſeriouſneſs</hi> ſhould not be drawn out of us likewiſe (as it hath been out of the hearts of God's people before us) by <hi>a delight</hi> in this ſervice.</p>
            <p>But you ſay, <hi>[When we know before-hand, that we have no more to doe but read a Prayer or Homily, we ſhall ordinarily be in danger of letting our minds goe another way, and think of other matters, and be ſenſeleſs of the work in hand.]</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I have read of an <note n="*" place="margin">Trithem. <hi>ad regul. c.</hi> 4. <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct.</hi> 57.</note> 
               <hi>Abbot</hi> who was ſomewhat of your opinion, ſaying, <hi>Orationes conſcriptas in chartis, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus infirmis utile eſt ut legant: fortioribus autem &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectioribus non convenit, niſi interdum pro ariditate cordis irriganda; quia illa oratio maximè efficaciam habet, non quam Calamus ſculpſit, ſed quam Mens ipſa formavit.</hi> But
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:95494:24"/> he ſpeaks of <hi>private</hi> Prayer; and even of that too, there are great <hi>Maſters</hi> of <hi>Devotion,</hi> (as they call them,) who obſerve, that 'tis neither the written <hi>Form,</hi> nor the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Fancy,</hi> that makes the <hi>difference,</hi> but the Affection. <hi>Oratio ab alio compoſita, quod ad ſe attinet, ornatior &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilior</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jacob. Alvarez de Paz, <hi>de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſ. pacis, l.</hi> 1. <hi>par.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. mihi <hi>pag.</hi> 168.</note> 
               <hi>eſſe conſuevit, tanquam à viris ſanctis &amp; ſpirituali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus edita. Quae ſi pari adfectu fundatur ac illa quam homo ex devotionis fervore enunciat, erit aequè perfecta: ſi mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus adfectûs &amp; devotionis habeat, imperfectior: ſi verò majori devotione proferatur, perfectior invenietur. Nam orationis vocalis ſublimitas ex parte Orantis, non ex ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate aut apta compoſitione verborum, vel ſubtilitate, ſed humilitate &amp; devotionis adfectu ejus qui orat, penſanda eſt.</hi> And that men ordinarily have no better attention to theſe <hi>Forms,</hi> of what kind ſoever, it is their own fault, in <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervaluing</hi> them, as well to God's dishonour as their own prejudice. <hi>Alii (quod mirum eſt) ſuavitate Orationis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ibid. Par.</hi> 2. <hi>in introduct. p.</hi> 83, 84.</note> 
               <hi>Mentalis illecti, Vocalem orationem tanquam minùs utilem curſim &amp; feſtinanter proferunt, ut plus temporis conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioni rerum coeleſtium impendant. Qui profectò minùs rectè conſiderant, cum conſideratione ſua, oratione vocali ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reverenter &amp; oſcitanter fusâ, ſe Deo diſplicere, &amp; ad Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem mentalem ineptos fieri minimè animadvertant.</hi> But have we <hi>no more</hi> to doe but <hi>read</hi> a Prayer? (for if you pleaſe, you may forbear your <hi>Homily,)</hi> Are we not therewithall concerned and tied to exerciſe our <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>affiance,</hi> our <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>reverence,</hi> our <hi>love, joy,</hi> and longing <hi>deſire</hi> of what we pray for? He that minds his <hi>duty,</hi> and puts theſe <hi>Ingredients</hi> into the Prayer he reads, will find no leiſure <hi>to think of other matters,</hi> nor can he be <hi>ſenſeleſs of the work in hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You proceed, <hi>[Though he is but an Hypocrite that is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on by no greater a motive then mans obſervation and approbation; yet is it a help not to be deſpiſed, when even</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:95494:25"/> 
               <hi>a neceſsity of avoiding juſt ſhame with men ſhall neceſſarily awake our invention, and all our faculties to their work, and be a concurrent help with Spiritual Motives.]</hi> We ſee you are content to <hi>plow</hi> with an <hi>Oxe</hi> and an <hi>Aſſe,</hi> rather then the <hi>ground</hi> you have <hi>laid down</hi> ſhould be untill'd; and to <hi>cloath</hi> the Controverſie you have eſpouſed with <hi>Linſey-woolſey,</hi> rather then it ſhould appear naked of <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>Reaſon.</hi> But take heed you make it not your great <hi>Motive</hi> to your <hi>Extemporary</hi> Conceptions (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the variety of <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>Occaſions)</hi> to be <hi>obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> and <hi>admired</hi> of men: If you do, our Saviour tells you, <hi>you have your reward;</hi> and I muſt tell you, you had better be without it, though, by this means, you can (as one of your Brethren boaſted that he did) <hi>break</hi> the Good wives <hi>hearts,</hi> and carry the <hi>pieces</hi> in your Pockets. But will <hi>ſhame</hi> with men <hi>neceſſarily</hi> awaken a mans inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? 'Tis more then <hi>ſhame with God</hi> and <hi>Hell torments</hi> can doe to many thouſands. But what if this <hi>concurrent help</hi> does awaken your <hi>invention?</hi> will you offer <hi>that</hi> for a ſacrifice in ſtead of Prayer? I have read of a people repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for going a <hi>whoring</hi> after their <hi>own Inventions:</hi> but never of a people commended for <hi>praying</hi> after their <hi>own inventions.</hi> Why? Prayer is <hi>a powring out of the heart,</hi> not the <hi>brain,</hi> an imployment of the <hi>Affections</hi> rather then the <hi>Phantaſie,</hi> of the <hi>Will</hi> rather then the <hi>Underſtanding. Cognitio Dei Scholaſtica ad intellectum praecipuè pertinet; Cognitio Dei myſtica</hi> (and 'tis that is uſeful in our prayers) <hi>non tam cognoſcere quàm amare quaerit, &amp; ad aſtringen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Deum amoris affectibus ſe extendit,</hi> ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">de Myſtica Theolog.</note> 
               <hi>Gerſon.</hi> True, the <hi>underſtanding</hi> hath its <hi>part</hi> in prayer; but yet <hi>Meditation</hi> and <hi>Prayer</hi> are <hi>two</hi> things. So thoſe that are accounted the great <hi>Maſters of Devotion</hi> tell us; <hi>Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever employment the mind or underſtanding exerciſeth in</hi> Prayer, <hi>by diſcourſing, inventing motives,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>theſe are</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:95494:25"/> 
               <hi>onely</hi> Preparations <hi>to prayer, and not</hi> Prayer it ſelf, <hi>which is onely and immediately exerciſed</hi> by the will <hi>or</hi> affections <hi>adhering to God,</hi> as <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>In Sanctae Soph.</hi> Treat. 3. §. 1. c. 1. pag. 6. nu. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtin Baker</hi> hath it. <hi>Meditatio docet quid de ſit; oratio quid de ſit obtinet: illa viam oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, iſta deducit. Meditatione denique agnoſcimus immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentia nobis pericula, oratione evadimus,</hi> ſaith S. <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Serm.</hi> 1. <hi>in die S. Andreae.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bernard.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>De vit. Spirit. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>part.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 31. <hi>(mihi) pag.</hi> 332. <hi>D.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Jacobus Alvar. de Paz.</hi> defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Prayer according to <hi>Damaſcen, [Petitio decentium à Deo]</hi> he addeth; <hi>Et quidem haec, ut fervens ſit, commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niter ex Meditatione progreditur. Nam poſtquam Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione didicimus quae nobis fugienda ſint vel amanda, viden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes non poſſe nos ſine Dei favore aut malum fugere aut bonum praeſtare, ad Orationem pro auxilii impetratione fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinamus.</hi> So that your wants may be ſumm'd up into a certain <hi>Form beforehand;</hi> and then, if your <hi>Invention</hi> becomes <hi>ſilent,</hi> your <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> will play their <hi>part</hi> with the more <hi>exactneſs</hi> and <hi>fervency,</hi> when (there being nothing to diſtract the other Faculties) they have it <hi>prick'd</hi> down in a <hi>Book</hi> before them.</p>
            <p>But you urge, that <hi>[Common experience tells us, that the beſt are apt to loſe a great deal of their Affection, by the conſtant uſe of the ſame words or Forms.]</hi> Which if under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the <hi>very</hi> beſt, is a very great falſhood; For our Bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> never prayed more <hi>earneſtly,</hi> then when he ſaid <hi>the ſame words,</hi> and repeated the <hi>ſame form</hi> of <note place="margin">Luke 22. 44. with Mat. 26. 44. Pſal. 42. 1, 2.</note> Prayer. And the <hi>Royall</hi> Prophet cryes out, <hi>As the Hart panteth after the water-brooks, ſo panteth my ſoul after thee, O God. My ſoul thirſteth for God, for the living God: when ſhall I come and appear before God? Cupio &amp; ſitio cultum Dei mei viventis,</hi> as <hi>Theodoret</hi> doth expound it. And yet that was a <hi>ſet courſe</hi> of <hi>worſhip.</hi> And again, <hi>How amiable</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 84. 1, 2, 4.</note> 
               <hi>are thy tabernacles, O Lord of Hoſts! My ſoul longeth, yea even fainteth for the Courts of the Lord: my heart and my fleſh cryeth out for the living God. Bleſſed be they that</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:95494:26"/> 
               <hi>dwell in thy houſe, they will be ſtill praiſing thee:</hi> and yet, in thoſe days, their <hi>Solemn</hi> Service was not made up of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary conceptions,</hi> but of <hi>ſet Forms</hi> of <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> &amp;c. to expreſs and entertain their affections. Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſung that Hymn at his Paſſeover which was cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſung amongſt the Jews at their Paſchal devotions, as <hi>Beza</hi> doth acknowledge. And <hi>Revel.</hi> 15. 3. They ſing the <hi>old</hi> Song of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and I hope without any allay to their affection.</p>
            <p>But from affirmations you come to inſtance thus; <hi>[Let the ſame Sermon be preached an hundred times over, and try whether an hundred for one will not be much leſs moved by it then they were at firſt.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs it may be ſo: but here we have <hi>non cauſam pro cauſa,</hi> you put a fallacy upon your ſelves as well as upon your Reader: For this happens not through the <hi>Identity</hi> of the diſcourſe, but through the <hi>defeat</hi> of the Hearer. Man's phantaſy deſires novelty, and in a <hi>Sermon</hi> he looks to be entertained with ſome <hi>variety;</hi> but finding his <hi>expectation deceived,</hi> he becomes <hi>unſatisfied,</hi> if not moved (otherwiſe then at the <hi>firſt</hi> hearing of the ſame diſcourſe) with <hi>indignation:</hi> but let a man out of <hi>choice</hi> read the <hi>ſame</hi> Sermon never ſo often over, for the <hi>ſetling</hi> of his <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>direction</hi> of his <hi>Duty,</hi> and he will find that his ſatisfaction will be improved. Otherwiſe it would be adviſable to diſſwade men from a <hi>frequency</hi> of reading the ſame <hi>Scripture,</hi> and receiving the ſame <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> for fear the <hi>frequentation</hi> ſhould make them <hi>nauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi> But of this <hi>Spiritual refection</hi> that of <hi>Syracides</hi> is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified to all <hi>truly devout</hi> Souls, <hi>Qui edunt me, adhuc eſuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; &amp; qui bibunt me, adhuc ſitient,</hi> They that eat hereof <note place="margin">Ecclus. 24. 21./29.</note> do yet hunger; and they that drink thereof are yet thirſty. And he that finds it otherwiſe in himſelf, had need look to it; He hath <hi>ſomething</hi> in him that muſt be <hi>mortified.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:95494:26"/>
            <p>And our <hi>Diſſenters</hi> confeſs as much in their next words; for they tell us, <hi>[It is not only the common corruption of our nature, but ſomewhat of innocent infirmity, that is the cauſe of this; and man muſt ceaſe to be man, or to be mortal, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it will be otherwiſe.]</hi> So far as our <hi>Corruption</hi> is in fault, we muſt take care (as I was ſaying) to have it morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; and for our <hi>common</hi> incident <hi>Infirmities,</hi> they may be help'd by wholſome methods and preſcriptions. <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſianus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>De inſtit. cap.</hi> 20.</note> tells us, that in his time there was wont to be ſo ſtrict a ſilence and attention at the Celebration of the Publick <hi>Synaxes,</hi> that you would have thought there had been never a man preſent but he that did <hi>officiate.</hi> And even while their City was beſieged, the <hi>Jewes</hi> were ſo <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joſeph. <hi>de Bello Judaico lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> upon their <hi>Sacred Service,</hi> that <hi>Plurimi ſacerdotum, quanquam hoſtes ſtrictis gladiis irruentes videbant, intre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidi tamen in peragendis rebus divinis perſeverabant; &amp; in ipſo libandi templúm<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> adolendi miniſterio mactabantur, ſaluti quoque praeferentes Religionis obſequium.</hi> When the enemies ruſhed in upon them with their naked ſwords, the Prieſts went on in their holy Office; and preferring the duties of their Religion before their Lives, they were ſlain in the very exerciſe of their Miniſtery. When the <hi>Prieſt</hi> ſummons the attention of the people by that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, <hi>Surſum corda,</hi> Lift up your hearts, if they anſwer his invitation in ſincerity, <hi>Habemus ad Dominum,</hi> We lift them up unto the Lord, their attention is unblamable. And that we may be the better diſpoſed to carry ſuch an atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the <hi>ſacred</hi> office, we ſhould reflect upon our ſelves to get a <hi>ſenſe</hi> of our own <hi>indignity</hi> and baſeneſſe; and look up to God, to gain a lively apprehenſion of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Majeſty:</hi> and while we duely ponder our <hi>diſtance</hi> from him and our <hi>guiltineſs</hi> before him, this Conſideration will beget <hi>Reverence,</hi> that Reverence will beget <hi>Attention,</hi> and that Attention will not fail to produce <hi>Devotion</hi> in us.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:95494:27"/>
            <p>For ſuch incident <hi>Evagations</hi> and diſtractions of mind as are <hi>involuntary</hi> and <hi>inevitable,</hi> they will never be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted (for ſin) to us, if we may believe <note n="*" place="margin">2<hi>
                     <hi rend="sup">a</hi>.</hi> 2ae. <hi>q.</hi> 83. <hi>a.</hi> 13. <hi>ad</hi> 3<hi>
                     <hi rend="sup">m</hi>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Aquinas,</hi> or <hi>Baſil</hi> in him: <hi>Si debilitatus à peccato fixè nequis orare, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumcunque potes teipſum cohibeas, &amp; Deus ignoſcet: eo quòd non ex negligentia, ſed ex fragilitate, non potes, ut oportet, aſsiſtere coram Deo,</hi> If thou wanteſt that fixation of Spirit which thou deſireſt in thy prayers, God will par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don it; becauſe it proceedeth not out of negligence, but of frailty. We had better give ſuch <hi>innocent infirmities a toleration,</hi> then ſeek to remove them by a <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal;</hi> and ſuch will be our Diſobedience.</p>
            <p>There are ſome other <hi>infirmities</hi> that would be thought of too, though in themſelves very <hi>innocent.</hi> Whereas the Soul hath <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cum omnes potentiae anima in una eſſentia animae radicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; neceſſe eſt quod quando u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na potentia in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenditur in ſuo actu, altera in ſuo actu remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur, vel etiam totaliter in ſuo actu impedia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: tum quia omnis virtus ad plura diſperſa fit minor, unde è contrario quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do intenditur circa unum, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus poteſt ad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia diſpergi; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um quia in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perationibus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimae requiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur quaedam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentio, quae dum vehementer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicatur ad unum, non poteſt alteri vehementer attendere.</hi> Tho. 1. 2. q. 77. ar. 1. in corp.</note> ſundry <hi>Faculties</hi> and <hi>Operations;</hi> we find by common <hi>Experience,</hi> that we are not able <hi>intenſively</hi> to actuate them all at <hi>once.</hi> When the <hi>Intellect</hi> doth moſt <hi>earneſtly pore</hi> upon an Object, to make a Speculation of its <hi>truth,</hi> the <hi>Will</hi> is taken off, or infeebled in her <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> and grows <hi>remiſs</hi> to love and embrace the <hi>goodneſs</hi> of it. <hi>And man muſt ceaſe to be man, or to be mortal, before it will be otherwiſe.</hi> Now foraſmuch as the <hi>Will and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections</hi> are the moſt <hi>immediate active</hi> inſtruments of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion (from which it hath as well its <hi>worth</hi> as its <hi>being)</hi> and foraſmuch as <hi>theſe</hi> can act more <hi>earneſtly</hi> and fix more <hi>ſtedfaſtly</hi> upon holy Objects, the leſs the Soul is drawn off by the <hi>invention</hi> and the <hi>diſcourſings</hi> of the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; hence it follows that <hi>Common Forms</hi> (in which the ſubject-matter of the Prayer with ſuitable <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> and <hi>Arguments</hi> are ſo digeſted, that the <hi>Phantaſy</hi> and <hi>Underſtanding</hi> have nothing to doe, but to reflect upon them, and <hi>quietly</hi> to propound them to the <hi>Will)</hi> are of huge advantage to Devotion.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:95494:27"/>
            <p>By this means therefore we ſee <hi>Devotion</hi> hath been kept up, and kept alive in the <hi>Church</hi> in moſt, if not in all, Ages. And the <hi>benefit</hi> hereof, becauſe more diſcernible towards them, is <hi>generally</hi> acknowledged in reference to the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Orationes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptas in char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, mentibus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmis utile eſt ut legant.</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>them. <hi>ut ſupra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Weakeſt</hi> (which makes up the far greateſt number) of Chriſtians. And therefore, whereas you conclude, <hi>[that the nature of the thing and the common experience of your own diſpoſitions, and of the effect upon others, aſſureth you, that</hi> underſtanding ſerious Godlineſs <hi>is like to be extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, if</hi> onely <hi>Forms be allowed in the Church, on pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of extinguiſhing Errours and Diviſions;]</hi> we muſt take the liberty to tell you, that as well the experience of <hi>our own diſpoſitions,</hi> as the <hi>conſtant</hi> Practice of the <hi>Church</hi> in all Ages, aſſures us the contrary. Hereupon we are aſtoniſhed no leſſe at the <hi>untruth</hi> and <hi>perverſity,</hi> then at the <hi>arrogance</hi> of your following expreſſions, in theſe vain words, <hi>[And though we have concurred to offer you our more Corrected</hi> Nepenthe's, <hi>yet muſt we, before God and men, proteſt againſt the</hi> doſe <hi>of</hi> Opium <hi>which you here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe or wiſh for, as that which plainly tendeth to cure the Diſeaſe by the extinguiſhing of Life, and to unite us all in a dead Religion.]</hi> You need not force your modeſty to tell us, (we know your opinion well enough) that your own <hi>Geeſe</hi> are all <hi>Swans:</hi> but we like none of the <hi>breed,</hi> for their <hi>black</hi> feet ſake, which trample down all <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Authority.</hi> But your <hi>Nepenthe's</hi> haply are not ſo proper for your Conſtitutions: Things that do exhilarate and raiſe the Spirits, and awaken Fancy, are dangerous to be adminiſtred to the <hi>Frantick.</hi> And it is an ill <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Apud medicos</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur affectus praeter natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, qui mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum, velut um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra corpus, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur.</hi> Galen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</note> 
               <hi>Symptome,</hi> that you proclaim your <hi>medicine</hi> to be your <hi>poiſon:</hi> but, if (finding you in ſome <hi>Lucid interval)</hi> we can perſuade you to take it, that <hi>doſe</hi> of <hi>Opium</hi> will be more ſoveraign to <hi>coole</hi> your <hi>brain,</hi> and bring you to <hi>reſt,</hi> and <hi>ſettle</hi> your diſtempers.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:95494:28"/>
            <p>For you <hi>talke idly</hi> ſtill, in your next words, <hi>[And when our Prayers that avail muſt be effectual and fervent,</hi> Jam. 5. 6. <hi>and God will be worſhipped in Spirit and truth, and more regardeth the frame of the Heart then the Comelineſs of Expreſsion; we have no reaſon to be taken with any thing that pretends to help the Tongue, while we are ſure it ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily hurts the Heart.]</hi> So you ſay: but are you ſure on't? Will you not <hi>eate</hi> your words preſently, and tell us, that <hi>Formes have their laudable uſe?</hi> We ſhall obſerve it as we go along with you. In the interim we do acknowledge, that it is not the <hi>ſtyle</hi> and <hi>ornament,</hi> but the <hi>humility</hi> and the <hi>fervour,</hi> that gives the perfection unto Prayer: And Prayer is then <hi>humble</hi> and <hi>fervent,</hi> not when 'tis <hi>deſigned</hi> and <hi>made</hi> to <hi>move</hi> affection (as your <hi>extemporary</hi> ones for the moſt part are) but when it proceeds from it, as the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of a heart that abounds with humility, fervour and compunction. Hence <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Grad.</hi> 21.</note> 
               <hi>Climacus</hi> adviſeth, <hi>Noli verbis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultioribus in oratione tua uti. Saepe enim Infantium ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicia, &amp; pura, &amp; balbutientia verba Patrem ſuum qui in coelis eſt placaverunt.</hi> But he ſpeaks of the Prayer, not of a <hi>Publick,</hi> but a <hi>Private</hi> perſon, offer'd up in his <hi>own name,</hi> and not in the <hi>name</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi> For ſhould the Prieſt offer up thoſe <hi>ſimplicia</hi> and <hi>balbutientia verba,</hi> thoſe Childiſh uncouth expreſſions <hi>there,</hi> he would certainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre a juſt ſhame with men, and ſo loſe that <hi>concurrent help</hi> which you formerly commended to us. But what? cannot a <hi>Form</hi> of Prayer be <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>God forbid that I ſhould ever think that there are not righteous men among the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latical, or fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent effectual prayers that are Liturgical;</hi> ſaith your Advocate, in his <hi>Peaceable Enquiry</hi> about <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination,</hi> p. 125.</note> 
               <hi>effectual and fervent,</hi> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>James</hi> requires? cannot God be worſhipped <hi>in Spirit and in truth</hi> in it? If you <hi>affirm,</hi> then you produce theſe Scriptures to no purpoſe: but if you <hi>deny,</hi> then it will follow that no forms are <hi>laudable;</hi> and then you <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict</hi> your ſelves, and <hi>condemn</hi> as well <hi>God</hi> himſelf as his Servants for preſcribing them.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:95494:28"/>
            <p>But for all you have involved your ſelves in theſe pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable Abſurdities, you are reſolved to hold the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſtill; for you ſay further, <hi>[It is not the affirmations of any men in the world, perſuading us of the harmeleſneſs of ſuch a courſe, that can ſo far unman us, as to make us disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve both our own Experience, and common Obſervation of the effect on others.]</hi> We know, <hi>Humanum eſt errare,</hi> and if you will not be <hi>unman'd</hi> in that ſenſe, who can help it? 'Tis certain, men may be deceived in their <hi>own</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">What think you of <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biram?</hi> Numb. 16. 3. <hi>All the congregation are holy, every one of them, and the Lord is among them: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then lift ye up your ſelves above the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the Lord?</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience</hi> and in thoſe <hi>effects</hi> which they obſerve in others. There is a <hi>ſenſible Devotion</hi> that begins in <hi>ſenſitive nature,</hi> and makes a conſpicuous alteration in <hi>it.</hi> It produces great <hi>tenderneſſes, fervour</hi> and <hi>melting affections;</hi> it will draw <hi>ſighs</hi> from the boſom, and <hi>tears</hi> from the eies, and ſpring many motions of <hi>delectation and ſweetneſs</hi> in the heart. And men may have ſo great a <hi>complacency</hi> in theſe <hi>inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations</hi> of ſweetneſs and pleaſing <hi>impetuoſities</hi> (imagining them to be gracious <hi>effects</hi> and actuations of the Holy Ghoſt) as to be <hi>tranſported</hi> with them. And yet this <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Devotion</hi> may rather indanger to depreſſe the <hi>opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> then advance them; and many times doth nouriſh <hi>Pride, ſelf-love,</hi> and a <hi>contempt of others,</hi> rather then contribute to the augmentation of <hi>Divine Love,</hi> or a proficiency in <hi>Obedience.</hi> To abate therefore the too high <hi>eſteem</hi> that unwary ſouls may have of this <hi>ſenſible fervour and devotion,</hi> we are informed by very <note n="*" place="margin">Jacob. Alvarez. de Paz, <hi>de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſ. Pacis lib.</hi> 2. <hi>par.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>per totum.</hi> Sancta Sophia <hi>Treat.</hi> 3. §. 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>per totum. Dr.</hi> Meric Caſaubon <hi>of Enthuſiaſm, c.</hi> 6. <hi>per totum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>creditable</hi> obſervation, that <hi>it</hi> is not alwaies a ſign of a good diſpoſition or holineſs in the Soul. Very <hi>impious</hi> perſons may, and have injoyed it. When it is derived to us as the <hi>gift</hi> of God, he intends it for our <hi>incouragement</hi> in his pure love; and therefore it is not to be neglected. <hi>Hae conſolationes ſenſibiles</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Senſible devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> are called alſo <hi>ſenſible conſolations,</hi> by the Writers of Myſtical Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy.</note> 
               <hi>verae, quamvis deſpiciendae non ſint, non ſunt tamen ſupra modum aſtimandae. Quia nec ſunt verae virtutes, nec neceſsarii ſolidarum virtutum</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:95494:29"/> 
               <hi>effectus, nec neceſſaria profectûs inſtrumenta, ſine quibus plurimi ad magnam virtutem ac mentis puritatem aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c. Alvar. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note>. When they are <hi>truly</hi> ſent us from God, they are ſubject to great <hi>perverſities;</hi> if they be not uſed with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, <hi>they</hi> may prove pernicious, and plunge the Soul <note place="margin">Auguſt. Baker. <hi>in Sanct. Soph. ubi ſuprá.</hi>
               </note> more deeply in <hi>ſelf-love</hi> and <hi>corrupt nature,</hi> (in which <hi>they</hi> are much immerſed.) But this <hi>ſenſible Devotion,</hi> fervour and ſweetneſſe, may flow alſo from the mere <hi>natural temper</hi> of the body, or from the <hi>vehement intention</hi> of the mind, or from a <hi>tone</hi> and <hi>cadence</hi> of words, or <hi>power</hi> of <hi>lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,</hi> or from the <hi>ſubtile inſinuation</hi> and <hi>illuſion</hi> of the Devil; as the <hi>Maſters</hi> of <hi>Devotions</hi> do generally obſerve.</p>
            <p>This is a Truth acknowledged in <hi>the Morning Exerciſe at Cripplegate,</hi> (p. 515.) where it is reſolved, That <hi>we may eaſily be deceived by our</hi> Enlargements, <hi>becauſe there are many</hi> winds <hi>and</hi> gales <hi>blowing from ſeveral quarters, which may ſet the Soul in</hi> active <hi>going and doing; as</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular <hi>applauſe, high</hi> opinions <hi>of the Preacher,</hi> taking-Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions <hi>in Prayer, flouriſhing</hi> Novelties <hi>and notions in a Sermon,</hi> Satanical <hi>infuſions, common and ordinary</hi> Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>of the Holy Ghoſt, vouchſafed to</hi> Reprobates, Hebr. 6. 4, 5, 6. <hi>All which, or any of which, may ſo draw and delight the heart, that (as</hi> Orpheus<hi>'s Pipe) they may make the heart dance in a duty; and yet for all this, it may be poſsible, yea probable, the heart may dance after the Devil's pipe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you muſt give other men leave to have their <hi>own experience</hi> and <hi>obſervation</hi> as well as you. And when we ſee in you more <hi>Humility, Self-denial, Reſignation of will and ſelf-conceit,</hi> and more <hi>obedience to Superiours,</hi> (which are under a divine command, and of indiſpenſable neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to Salvation) we ſhall be the more inclinable to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve your pretenſions, that ſome proficiency in the way of <hi>ſolid</hi> Vertue and <hi>Devotion</hi> is to be made by the courſe you plead for. But it is not the <hi>affirmations</hi> of all the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:95494:29"/> men in the world, ſpeaking in their <hi>own</hi> behalf and in favour of their own <hi>conceits,</hi> that can ſo far <hi>unman</hi> us, as to make us interpret thoſe <hi>practices</hi> to be the <hi>effects</hi> of the Holy Spirit which <hi>contradict</hi> the Principles of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> extinguiſhing both Charity and Obedience.</p>
            <p>But admit the <hi>effects</hi> you boaſt of were <hi>really</hi> the <hi>gifts</hi> of God, and truly tended to the advancement of his <hi>pure</hi> Love in you: would this warrant you to contemn or omit the eſtabliſhed <hi>Liturgie</hi> of the Church? All the <hi>Maſters</hi> of Devotion, that I have met withall, do reſolve otherwiſe. To this purpoſe conſider what <hi>Auguſtin Baker</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sanct. Soph. <hi>ubi ſuprà, cap.</hi> 2.</note> ſaith in his Treatiſe of <hi>Vocal Prayer. As for that</hi> Vocal <hi>Prayer,</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>either in</hi> Publick <hi>or</hi> Private, <hi>which is by the lawes of the Church</hi> of obligation, <hi>no manner of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of finding more profit by</hi> internal <hi>exerciſes ought to be eſteemed a ſufficient ground for any to</hi> neglect <hi>or</hi> diſparage <hi>it. For though ſome Souls of the</hi> beſt <hi>diſpoſition might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps more advance themſelves towards</hi> perfection <hi>by</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal <hi>exerciſes</hi> alone: <hi>yet ſince generally, even in</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <hi>Souls are ſo</hi> tepid <hi>and</hi> negligent, <hi>that if they were left to their own voluntary devotions, they would ſcarce ever exerciſe either</hi> Vocal <hi>or</hi> Mental <hi>Prayer; therefore inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as a manifeſt</hi> diſtinction <hi>cannot be made between the Particular diſpoſitions of Perſons, it was requiſite and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, that</hi> all <hi>ſhould be obliged to a</hi> Publick <hi>external perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of</hi> divine Service, <hi>praiſing God with the tongues alſo (which were for that end given us;) that ſo an</hi> Order <hi>and</hi> decorum <hi>might be obſerved in God's</hi> Church, <hi>to the end it might imitate the imployment of</hi> Angels <hi>and glorified</hi> Saints, <hi>in a ſolemn</hi> united <hi>joyning of hearts and tongues to glorify God. This was neceſſary alſo for the</hi> edification <hi>and</hi> invitation <hi>of thoſe who are not obliged to the</hi> Office, <hi>who perhaps would never think of God, were they not incouraged thereto by ſeeing good Souls ſpend the greateſt part of their</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:95494:30"/> 
               <hi>time in ſuch</hi> ſolemn <hi>and allmoſt</hi> hourly <hi>praying to, and praiſing God.</hi> Thus he.</p>
            <p>And this, perhaps, you may be induced to ſubſcribe to, if we can get you <hi>in a good mood,</hi> as you now ſeem to be; for you tell us, in your next words, that <hi>[ſome Formes have their laudable uſe, to cure the errour and vice that lyeth on the other extream.]</hi> It ſeems then there is a <hi>Medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity,</hi> and now you are reſolved to <hi>hit</hi> it. In good time; for hitherto you have done more then inſinuate, That <hi>Formes</hi> are not a worſhip of God <hi>in Spirit and truth,</hi> not <hi>effectuall and fervent:</hi> but <hi>a dead Religion;</hi> that <hi>ordinarily they hurt the heart;</hi> that they are a <hi>doſe</hi> of <hi>Opium,</hi> that doth extinguiſh <hi>underſtanding-ſerious-godlineſs, and the life of Religion.</hi> What could you have ſaid more to load <hi>them</hi> with contempt? yet now you confeſs, <hi>ſome Forms</hi> are not only lawful, but <hi>laudable.</hi> This looks like <hi>Bellarmine</hi>'s <hi>[Tutiſsimum,]</hi> that gave a defeat to his whole deſigne. He writes five Books againſt <hi>Juſtification</hi> by Faith, and then concludes the <hi>Controverſie</hi> with a <hi>Confutation</hi> of all that he had written of it <hi>[Propter incertitudinem propriae juſtitiae, &amp; periculum inanis gloriae,</hi> Tutiſſimum <hi>eſt, fidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciam totam in ſola Dei miſericordia &amp; benignitate reponere.]</hi> So our <hi>Deformaliſts,</hi> after a miſerable <hi>ſtuctuation,</hi> are glad to come to an <hi>Anchor,</hi> to their <hi>Tutiſsimum,</hi> and to take fanctuary from an impendent ſtorm, by confeſſing that <hi>ſome Forms are Lawful.</hi> Lawfull; but for what? for nothing but to make a <hi>medicine</hi> to kill the <hi>itch,</hi> that of <hi>pride, curioſity,</hi> and <hi>novelty, [the errour and vice that lyeth on the other extream.]</hi> 'Tis well <hi>Forms</hi> are good for <hi>ſomething</hi> in your opinion. But let a <hi>wiſe</hi> and an <hi>humble</hi> man uſe them, and <hi>they</hi> will ſerve very well to entertain and exerciſe a ſound <hi>Faith,</hi> and a ſincere <hi>Love,</hi> and a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial <hi>Devotion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by this we ſee <hi>theſe</hi> men can ſpeak truth, if they
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:95494:30"/> liſt, eſpecially when <hi>their reputation</hi> and intereſt is concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in it; witneſs that Poſition of Mr <hi>Baxter</hi>'s, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>In his</hi> Unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury Volume <hi>againſt Mr.</hi> Crandon, <hi>or his</hi> Noſegay <hi>preſented to Mr.</hi> Joſeph Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryll, <hi>(page</hi> 83.) <hi>ante finem.</hi>
               </note> which, if his Party had the conſcience to practiſe it, would put an end to our <hi>Diviſions,</hi> and ſettle us in a happy ſtate of <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie:</hi> for thus he ſaith, <hi>[Let me be bold to tell my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to my Brethren of the Miniſtry, that though I deny them to have either credit or Authority</hi> againſt <hi>the known</hi> Word <hi>of God, yet ſo great is their credit and Authority, even as Teachers &amp; Guides of the Church, in Cauſes</hi> agreeable <hi>to the</hi> Word, <hi>And in Cauſes to the people</hi> doubtful <hi>and</hi> unknown, <hi>and in Cauſes left by the</hi> Word <hi>to</hi> their <hi>determination, (the Word determining them but generally) that I think the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of</hi> this <hi>truth hath been the main cauſe of our ſad</hi> Confuſions <hi>and</hi> Schiſms <hi>in England, and that the</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters <hi>have been</hi> guilty of it, <hi>partly by an over-modeſt</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing <note place="margin">
                  <hi>An important truth falls from the pen of Mr.</hi> Baxter, <hi>if he could</hi> ſay and hold.</note> 
               <hi>their Authority, and partly by an indiſcreet</hi> oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>to the Papiſts errour of the</hi> Authority <hi>of the</hi> Church: <hi>and I think that till we have</hi> better <hi>taught, even our</hi> Godly <hi>people, what</hi> credit <hi>and</hi> obedience <hi>is due to their</hi> Teachers <hi>and</hi> Spiritual Guides, <hi>the Churches of</hi> England <hi>ſhall never have</hi> peace, <hi>or any good or eſtabliſht</hi> Order. <hi>I ſay again, we are</hi> broken <hi>for want of the knowledg of</hi> this <hi>truth, and till this be</hi> known, <hi>we ſhall never be well bound up and healed.]</hi> This is Mr <hi>Baxter</hi>'s ſober Conceſſion; and he thought it ſo <hi>ſignal a verity,</hi> when he wrote it, that he ſet a <hi>hand</hi> in the <hi>margent</hi> to <hi>remark</hi> it, and <hi>point</hi> it out to every Reader, as moſt <hi>worthy</hi> his obſervation. Let him <hi>preach</hi> the <hi>ſame</hi> Doctrine ſtill, and <hi>act</hi> accordingly, and I doubt not, the <hi>Liturgy</hi> of the Church will become a <hi>Laudable</hi> Form of Divine Service, and more frequented.</p>
            <p>But is it any <hi>uncharitable</hi> or <hi>raſh</hi> Cenſure to ſay, that <hi>He</hi> hath juſt cauſe to cry out againſt himſelf, <hi>(Video melio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra probôque, Deteriora ſequor,)</hi> when we ſee him ſo <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory</hi> to his <hi>Spiritual Guides,</hi> ſo <hi>croſs</hi> to his own <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:95494:31"/> ſetting himſelf in the <hi>breach</hi> induſtriouſly to prevent the <hi>cloſing</hi> of it? To this end he hath a <hi>new deviſe,</hi> in the next paſſage, which is recommended to us in theſe words, <hi>[And might we but ſometimes have the liberty to interpoſe ſuch words as are needful to call home and quicken attention and affection, we ſhould think that a convenient conjunction of</hi> both, <hi>might be a well-tempered means to the Conſtitutions of moſt.]</hi> It ſeems your Wit goes a <hi>Wool-gathering</hi> at the time of your devotion. But admit it does; is not the <hi>voice</hi> of a <hi>Publick Solemn Office</hi> loud enough to call it home, or can you not find a <hi>Rod</hi> to fetch it? Get a lively <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>conſcience</hi> of your <hi>duty,</hi> with an <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of that dreadfull <hi>Majeſty,</hi> which is alwaies <hi>preſent,</hi> to behold with how <hi>ſerious</hi> an affection and reverence you perform your <hi>homage</hi> to him; Try what effects that will work upon your <hi>Phantaſy.</hi> However we commend your <hi>modeſty,</hi> that you deſire <hi>but ſometimes</hi> to have the liberty <hi>to interpoſe</hi> ſuch words as are <hi>needful</hi> to <hi>call home and quicken atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and affection.</hi> But what? will a <hi>dead</hi> affection and a <hi>roving phantaſy</hi> ſerve God's turn or yours <hi>otherwhiles?</hi> Beſides, do you take notice that your affection is <hi>dull,</hi> and your Phantaſy a <hi>wandring,</hi> or do you not? If you do not, you have no occaſion of ſuch <hi>interjections;</hi> if you do, then <hi>now</hi> you are <hi>awakened,</hi> and you have nothing <hi>more</hi> to doe, but to be <hi>careful</hi> to go <hi>forward.</hi> He that apprehends that (out of his own oſcitancy and heedleſneſs) he hath <hi>ſtep'd aſide,</hi> and <hi>loytered</hi> in his journey, and yet <hi>deſcries</hi> his right way before him, does but <hi>trifle</hi> and wander <hi>more,</hi> in run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the next houſe to parly about his deviation. And what are thoſe <hi>needful words</hi> which you deſire the liberty to <hi>interpoſe,</hi> in the uſe of the <hi>Common Publick Form?</hi> Are they <hi>non-ſenſe,</hi> or <hi>ſignificant?</hi> If <hi>Non-ſenſe,</hi> then it will be ridiculous to interpoſe them; If <hi>Significant,</hi> then either they ſignify the <hi>ſame</hi> thing with the <hi>Form</hi> wherein you
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:95494:31"/> would <hi>inſert</hi> them, or ſomething elſe. If the <hi>ſame</hi> thing with the <hi>Form,</hi> why ſhould the <hi>Form</hi> be <hi>interrupted?</hi> why cannot you pray for the ſame thing in the ſame words, as did our Saviour? If they ſignifie ſomething elſe, (that is not in the <hi>Form,</hi> and yet you will <hi>interrupt</hi> the Form to <hi>interpoſe</hi> them,) in ſtead of <hi>quickening attention,</hi> you will raiſe a <hi>wonder,</hi> and give a <hi>ſcandal,</hi> and put the people into <hi>confuſion.</hi> And therefore 'tis your wiſeſt way to keep thoſe <hi>needful</hi> awakening words, as a <hi>Reſerve,</hi> to aſſiſt you in your <hi>private</hi> Cloſet; for the conjunction of ſuch <hi>crude</hi> interpoſitions with the <hi>Publick ſolemn Liturgy</hi> would be diſconvenient, they will never <hi>cotton</hi> well, nor doth God allow that his field ſhould be ploughed with an Ox and an Aſs yoak'd together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[But ſtill we ſee,</hi> (as you proceed in your Complaint) <hi>the world will run into extreams, whatever be ſaid or done to hinder it.]</hi> And they that can run <hi>faſter</hi> this way then <hi>your ſelves,</hi> for me, let them win the goale and wear the garland. But you ſeek to juſtifie your ſelves, (if you could) in your next lines, where you ſay <hi>[It is but lately that we were put to it, againſt one</hi> extream, <hi>to defend the lawfulneſs of a Form of Liturgy.]</hi> I perceive you would faine be reputed <hi>Medium Harmonicum;</hi> but the world knows, you have for a long while marr'd the <hi>Muſick</hi> of this Church by your jarring <hi>diſproportions.</hi> For who <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taught</hi> even your <hi>Godly</hi> people, what <hi>credit</hi> and <hi>obedience</hi> is due to their <hi>Spiritual Guides,</hi> but you? Who pulled down and diſgraced the <hi>Solemn Liturgy</hi> of the Church but you? That you were <hi>put to it, to defend the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Liturgie,</hi> was a <hi>neceſsity</hi> of your own <hi>creating,</hi> and you did but fight with your own <hi>ſhadow</hi> in that combate; for that <hi>extream</hi> was your own production, and we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve you cannot forbear to expreſſe a very <hi>fond</hi> affection towards it upon all occaſions in your diſcourſe. No, no,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:95494:32"/> We cannot be deluded by ſuch <hi>aquivocation;</hi> you never cordially eſpouſed the quarrel of a <hi>Liturgy:</hi> we perceive well enough where the ſhoe wrings you, (in your next words) when you tell us <hi>[Now on the other extream, it troubleth us that we are forced againſt</hi> you, <hi>even</hi> ſuch as you, <hi>to defend the uſe of ſuch prayers of the Paſtours of the Churches as are neceſſarily varied according to Subjects and Occaſions; while you would have no prayers at all in the Church but ſuch Preſcribed Forms.]</hi> Whether that <hi>redupli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of <hi>[you, even ſuch as you,]</hi> be an <hi>Emphaſis</hi> of reſpect or indignation, we ſhall not conſult Mr <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Grotian Religion</hi> to interpret it. But if to have no Prayers in the <hi>Publick Solemn Service</hi> of the Church but Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed <hi>Forms</hi> be one of your <hi>Extreams,</hi> we hope 'tis ſo onely in that <hi>ſenſe</hi> in which the <hi>Pythagoreans</hi> called Vertue <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an <hi>extremitie,</hi> for its <hi>ſupereminency</hi> and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; for we are ſure it is oppoſite to no <hi>moral</hi> Vertue. And yet if the <hi>Paſtors</hi> of the Churches (by them under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as the <hi>Ancients</hi> uſually do) ſhall in their Prudence think fit to <hi>vary</hi> the Forms upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, we are alwaies content to ſubmit to the variation: But that <hi>ſingle</hi> Presbyters ever had that <hi>Liberty</hi> of vary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>according</hi> to their own <hi>Phantaſies,</hi> we ſtedfaſtly deny. And we adde yet further, that the <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>Occaſions</hi> may be <hi>ſuch</hi> as <hi>in diſcretion</hi> are not fit to be inſerted into the <hi>Solemn Service</hi> of the Church. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi>'s thorne in the fleſh might have wounded the heart of an unwary <hi>weak</hi> Diſciple, if it had been inſerted into the Publick <hi>Liturgy.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">We could tell you of Tickets put up to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to beg their Pulpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prayers, which have been not onely very ſtrange, but very ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous; and he is a ſtranger to this City that hath not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it.</note> It is more <hi>ſafe</hi> and <hi>prudent</hi> to recommend ſome things to Almighty God in general expreſſions, then to inſiſt too <hi>particularly</hi> and poſitively upon them. Chriſt knew very well the <hi>chief</hi> and <hi>particular</hi> wants of his Diſciples, when they begg'd that <hi>form</hi> of Prayer of him; yet he deſcends not to any enumeration of thoſe particulars, but delivers
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:95494:32"/> the Form in <hi>General</hi> terms, becauſe it was for a <hi>Publick</hi> uſe and benefit. <hi>In petendis à Deo beneficiis ſaepe erramus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Roſignolius <hi>de Diſciplina Chriſtianae Perfectionis, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>nec in hiſce rebus Deo quaſi precum vis eſt adferenda, ſed liberum illi permittendum, ut nos quò libuerit maximè im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellat. Fieri enim ſaepe ſolet, ut Deus iis qui hac animi diſpoſitione carent quod petunt impertiatur, quod tamen ipſis ruinae poſtea ſit occaſio. Quare</hi> Diaboli <hi>videtur eſſe ad certaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ejuſmodi rerum intempeſtivas efflagitationes incitare.</hi> To this we may adde that of <hi>De la Cerda. Petere pro ſeipſo</hi> tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralia, <hi>quamvis unicui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> eatenus <hi>liceat quatenus per talem petitionem fatemur Deum omnium</hi> authorem <hi>&amp;</hi> proſpecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, <hi>eique nos ſubmittimus, ea efflagitantes quae nobis ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniculo eſſe poſſunt ad virtutem &amp; ad ſuum ipſius cultum:</hi> tutius <hi>tamen eſt, nihil</hi> in particulari <hi>poſtulare, niſi</hi> ea <hi>quibus nullo modo poſſumus</hi> male <hi>uti, ut</hi> cor contritum &amp; humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, deduci in viam veritatis, &amp; in ſemitam mandatorum Dei, <hi>&amp;</hi> fimilia. <hi>Caetera verò, quorum</hi> bonus <hi>poteſt eſſe &amp;</hi> malus <hi>uſus, ſub</hi> generali <hi>nomine petenda ſunt, ut docebat</hi> Socrates, <hi>dicens,</hi> Bona à Deo petamus, <hi>hoc eſt, ſub hoc</hi> generali <hi>nomine,</hi> Da quae nobis bona ſunt. <hi>Quantumvis enim</hi> conditione <hi>moderetur petitio noſtra, dicentes,</hi> ſi fuerit voluntas tua; <hi>ſemper tamen</hi> latet anguis in herba, <hi>hoc eſt,</hi> voluntas noſtra <hi>in illa conditione,</hi> aviditaſque <hi>impetrandi, quod</hi> noſtra <hi>eſt voluptas.</hi> De la Cerda <hi>in Epiſt. ad Rome c.</hi> 8. §. 74. <hi>ad haec verba</hi> [Nam quid oremus ſicut oportet, neſcimus.]</p>
            <p>But you demand, <hi>[Why may we not adde, that whoſoever maketh the formes impoſed on us, if he uſe them, is guilty as well as we, of praying according to his private conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions?]</hi> For your ſatisfaction herein you might have remembred the old Rule, <hi>[Cum duo faciunt idem, non eſt idem:]</hi> What is compoſed as well by the direction as allowance of <hi>Authority,</hi> and is injoyned by it to be uſed, hath that <hi>ſacred</hi> ſtamp upon it, that doth ſufficiently di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh it from all <hi>private</hi> Conceptions.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:95494:33"/>
            <p>You adde in the laſt place, <hi>[We never ſaw it proved from Scripture, that Chriſt appointed any to ſuch an office, as to make Prayers for other Paſtours and Churches to offer up to God: and that this being none of the works of the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick or common Miniſterial office in the Primitive Church, is no work of any office of Divine Inſtitution.]</hi> That <hi>God</hi> made <hi>Forms</hi> of <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Bleſsing</hi> for the uſe of the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Prieſthood</hi> is evident, <hi>Numb.</hi> 6. 23, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Ecclus. 50. 20.</note> &amp;c. <hi>Luk.</hi> 11. 2. That <hi>David</hi> and other Holy <hi>Prophets</hi> were <hi>inſpired</hi> of God for <hi>that</hi> work, cannot be denied; or if it ſhould, we may prove it by theſe inſtances. 1. Officers are deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. 16, 17. And 2. their <hi>office</hi> (to celebrate the <hi>Solemn</hi> Service of God <hi>morning</hi> and <hi>evening)</hi> is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23. 30. And 3. <hi>this office</hi> did not conſiſt of <hi>extemporary Conceptions,</hi> but of <hi>ſet</hi> &amp; <hi>preſcribed Forms,</hi> penn'd by ſuch perſons as were endow'd with <hi>Gifts</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with <hi>Authority</hi> to doe it: as may eaſily be evinced from the very <hi>Titles</hi> of theſe <hi>Pſalms; Pſal.</hi> 4. <hi>[To the chief Muſician on Neginoth,</hi> A Pſalm of <hi>David]</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">That is, ſaith <hi>Deodati,</hi> Publiſhed by <hi>David,</hi> for the <hi>uſe</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> though it was penn'd before upon ſome <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular occaſion.</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. the <hi>Title</hi> is [A Pſalm <hi>of Aſaph]</hi> a famous Muſician in <hi>David</hi>'s daies, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25. 2. who was alſo a <hi>Prophet</hi> and Compoſer of <hi>Pſalms,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. 30. <q rend="inline"> Whereupon (ſaith <hi>Deodati)</hi> it is not certain whether the <hi>Pſalms</hi> which are <hi>intituled</hi> by his name were compoſed by <hi>him,</hi> or whether they were onely <hi>directed</hi> to him and his ſucceſſors, to be <hi>plaid</hi> and <hi>ſung</hi> in their turns by the holy Muſick. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102. the <hi>Title</hi> is <hi>[A Prayer of the afflicted, when he is overwhelmed, and powreth out his complaint before the Lord.]</hi>
               </q> 
               <q rend="inline"> It is apparent, ſaith <hi>Deodati,</hi> that <hi>this</hi> Pſalm was penned towards the end of the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Captivity, <hi>to be a Form of Prayer for the reſtauration of God's people,</hi> according to his promiſe.</q>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:95494:33"/> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92. the <hi>Title</hi> is <hi>[A Pſalm</hi> or <hi>Song for the Sabbath day]</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">that is, ſaith <hi>Deodati,</hi> to be <hi>ſolemnly</hi> ſung in the <hi>holy Aſſemblyes</hi> upon the <hi>Sabbath day.</hi>
               </q> From <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120. to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 134. <hi>(incluſivè)</hi> there are 15. Pſalms which are intitled <hi>[Pſalms of Degrees.]</hi> 
               <q rend="inline"> Which <hi>Title,</hi> ſaith <hi>Deo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dati,</hi> is of very obſcure and doubtfull ſignification; yet the likelyeſt opinion is, that theſe Pſalms were either newly penned, or choſen out from amongſt the old ones, to be <hi>ſung</hi> by the people in their return from <hi>Babylon,</hi> in their ſeveral daies journeys or ſtages as they tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled, either one or more, or all at every removing. Others ſay they were <hi>ſo</hi> ſtyled, becauſe they were wont to be ſung upon thoſe fifteen <hi>ſteps</hi> which were between the mens <hi>Court</hi> and that of the Prieſts.</q> However we are ſure they are <hi>Forms</hi> of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> of <hi>Praiſe,</hi> or <hi>Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Thanksgiving:</hi> and then, if you will allow the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers</hi> of them to be of God's <hi>appointment,</hi> we have even <hi>in Scripture</hi> found ſome <hi>appointed by Chriſt to ſuch an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice as to make Prayers for other Paſtours and Churches to offer up to God.</hi> And may we not find the like in the <hi>New Teſtament? Erant nonnulli apud priſcos illos Chriſtianae</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Theophylact. <hi>in</hi> 1 <hi>ad Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth. cap.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>fidei ſectatores qui ſupplicandi gratiam linguâ exciperent,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Quinetiam Pſalmos ex priſcis illis nonnulli per ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talem gratiam componebant. Cum pleraque eorum quae nobis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem ad Rom.</hi> 8. 26.</note> 
               <hi>proſint ignorantes inutilia peteremus, accedebat orationis chariſma uni cuidam eorum qui tum vixerunt, &amp; quod com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muniter omnibus conferebat, ipſe ſtans precabatur, alioſque id petere docebat.</hi> And that theſe <hi>Pſalms</hi> and <hi>Prayers</hi> were intended for the uſe and benefit of God's Church we may conclude from the whole diſcourſe of the Apoſtle. And when that Apoſtle gives ſo ſtrict a charge, <hi>[Let all things be done decently and in order; let all things be done to the glory of God; let all things be done to edification;]</hi> Is not the duty of <hi>ordering</hi> all things according to this <hi>Rule</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:95494:34"/> incumbent upon the <hi>Governours</hi> of the Church? Doth he not ſay <hi>perſonally</hi> to <hi>Titus, [For this cauſe left I thee in Crete, that thou ſhouldeſt ſet in order the things that are wanting?] Tit.</hi> 1. 5. And doth he not write to <hi>Timothy, [that firſt of all Supplications, Prayers, Interceſsions, and giving of Thanks be made for all men?]</hi> Is not <hi>Timothy</hi> the <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 1. See Mr <hi>Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dike</hi> of <hi>the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God in Publ. Aſs.</hi>
               </note> Biſhop incharged with <hi>this</hi> Office? and is not this a <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Order</hi> given to <hi>him,</hi> touching the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of <hi>Publick Prayer</hi> to be ſetled in all the <hi>Aſſemblies</hi> of his Juriſdiction? This therefore is a <hi>work</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> or <hi>common Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial office,</hi> and conſequently the <hi>work</hi> of an <hi>office of Divine Inſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But admit we had no ſuch warrant, either of <hi>expreſs Precept</hi> or <hi>clear Example,</hi> in Holy Scripture for this Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice: yet the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> thereof may be evinced upon theſe undeniable <hi>Principles,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Apoſtles intended <hi>Unity,</hi> and to that end re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Uniformity</hi> to the Churches. That they intended <hi>Unity</hi> is evident, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 1, 2, 3, &amp;c. <hi>I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the Priſoner of the Lord, beſeech you that ye walk wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the vocation wherewith ye are called; with all lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and meekneſs, with long ſuffering, forbearing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in love: endeavouring to keep the unity of the Spirit</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See 1 Cor. 1. 10. and Rom. 15. verſ. 5. 6. <hi>ut ſuprá.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in the bond of peace. There is one body, and one Spirit, even as ye are called in one hope of your calling: One Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm, one God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all.</hi> And <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 17. <hi>Now I beſeech you, brethren, mark them which cauſe diviſions and offences, contrary to the doctrine which ye have learned, and avoid them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That they recommended <hi>Uniformity</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that <hi>Unity,</hi> is no leſs evident; and upon this account, their <hi>Order</hi> was a Proſpect of ſo much pleaſure to the Great Apoſtle in the Church of the <hi>Coloſsians</hi> (Col. 2. 5.)
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:95494:34"/> 
               <hi>For though I be abſent in the fleſh, yet am I with you in the Spirit, joying and beholding</hi> your Order, <hi>and the</hi> Stedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>of your</hi> Faith <hi>in Chriſt</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide R. P. E. S.</hi> Jo. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. <hi>in Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</hi>
               </note>. When men begin to break <hi>Order,</hi> they grow <hi>looſe</hi> in their <hi>Faith</hi> both to God and man. This is the Firſt <hi>Principle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Apoſtles, at their <hi>firſt</hi> preaching of the Goſpel, did not eſtabliſh that <hi>Order</hi> which the <hi>State</hi> of the Church did <hi>afterwards</hi> require. This is evident, from thoſe <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees</hi> made in the firſt Council at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Act. 15. and from that of the Apoſtle, <hi>[The reſt will I ſet in order when I come.]</hi> The Second <hi>Principle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>They</hi> exſpected ſuch a <hi>ſettlement</hi> to be made by thoſe to whom they did intruſt the <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi> This is evident from S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtle to <hi>Titus,</hi> (Chap. 1. 5.) where he tells him, <hi>[For this cauſe left I thee in Crete, that thou ſhouldſt ſet in order the things that are left undone,</hi> (according to the Original.)] From which words theſe two things do naturally follow: 1. That, at his firſt preaching of the Goſpel S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> had left ſome things <hi>undone,</hi> which, even in his own judgment, were, afterwards, fit to be done, (which ſhews the vanity and falſhood of that pretenſion, That becauſe the Apoſtles did not eſtabliſh ſuch and ſuch things, therefore (forſooth) they did not think them convenient to be eſtabliſhed at all.) 2. (From hence it follows) That he exſpected the accompliſhment hereof from the care of <hi>Titus.</hi> The Third <hi>Principle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. They gave certain <hi>Canons</hi> or general <hi>Rules</hi> to direct the <hi>Governours</hi> of the Church in making ſuch Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Such are thoſe mentioned in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, <hi>Let all things be done to the glory of God; Let all things be done to edification; Let all things be done decently, and in order.</hi> Hereupon <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſtitut. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. §. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Calvin,</hi> writing of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions,</hi> doth acknowledge ſome of them to be lawful, <hi>ut</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:95494:35"/> 
               <hi>Dei verbo conſentaneae,</hi> as being conſonant to the Word of God. And <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>In confeſ. Fidei, cap.</hi> 5. §. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Beza</hi> ſaith, <hi>Neceſſe eſt ut in domo Dei om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia ordine fiant; cujus Ordinis una quidem eſt univerſalis ratio ex verbo Dei petenda, ſed non una &amp; eadem forma quibuſvis circumſtantiis conveniens:</hi> That is, <hi>It is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that in the houſe of God all things be done in Order; of which Order the one Univerſal Rule or Reaſon is to be taken out of the Word of God, though there be not one and the ſame form agreeing in all circumſtances.</hi> And again, <hi>Ejuſmodi</hi> 
               <note place="margin">§. 16.</note> 
               <hi>conſtitutiones,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quod attinet ad finem &amp; funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, nempe generale illud decorum quod nobis obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vandum praecipitur, divinae ſunt &amp; coeleſtes:</hi> That is, <hi>Such Conſtitutions, as to the end and foundation of them, to wit, that General</hi> Decorum <hi>which we are commanded to obſerve, are divine and celeſtial.</hi> The Fourth <hi>Principle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. They left it to the <hi>Judgment</hi> of the <hi>Governours</hi> of the Church to determine of the <hi>Particulars</hi> to be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed according to <hi>Theſe</hi> Rules. That the Church hath power to inſtitute External <hi>Rites,</hi> and preſcribe <hi>Forms,</hi> and to make <hi>Canons</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> to <hi>aſsiſt</hi> her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and <hi>regulate</hi> their <hi>Practice</hi> in the <hi>Publick</hi> Worſhip and Service of God, is the <hi>Confeſsion</hi> of All Churches. And this is conſonant to the <hi>Word</hi> of God too. For <hi>that</hi> Word, or God by it (which is all one) gives a charge to the <hi>Church</hi> (as hath been ſaid) <hi>to doe all things to Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Glory of God;</hi> and to this end, it injoyns <hi>her</hi> to perform all her Holy Offices <hi>decently</hi> and <hi>in order,</hi> and to worſhip God <hi>in the beauty of Holineſs.</hi> This the Word of God commands, but does not determine the <hi>Particulars</hi> wherein that <hi>Order, beauty</hi> &amp; <hi>decency</hi> do conſiſt. It follows therefore that <hi>This</hi> Word of God ſuppoſeth a <hi>Power</hi> in the Church to <hi>inſtitute</hi> Rites, and <hi>preſcribe</hi> Forms, and <hi>make</hi> Canons to <hi>this</hi> purpoſe. And where ſhal we find this power <hi>lodged</hi> by the Apoſtle, (at that time when there were no
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:95494:35"/> 
               <hi>Kings</hi> that were <hi>nurſing Fathers</hi> to the Church?) <hi>For this cauſe I left thee, (Titus,</hi> a <hi>ſingle</hi> Perſon, and at leaſt a <hi>Biſhop,) in Crete, that thou ſhouldſt ſet in</hi> order <hi>the things that are wanting,</hi> (Tit. 1. 5.) The Power and Authority is lodged in the Governours, that is, the Biſhops of the Church. The Fifth <hi>Principle.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Remember Mr <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Doctrine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, of the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of the Church.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. That all <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>Members</hi> of the Church are <hi>obliged</hi> in Conſcience to <hi>ſubmit</hi> to and <hi>obey</hi> ſuch <hi>Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</hi> For 'tis moſt certain, where <hi>ſome</hi> are impowered to command, <hi>others</hi> are injoyned to obey; elſe the <hi>Power</hi> given to <hi>Superiors</hi> would be to no effect. Hereupon <hi>Beza</hi> acknowledgeth, That although theſe <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions</hi> be <hi>Humane and mutable,</hi> and do not <hi>propriè per ſe,</hi> properly by themſelves <hi>bind the Conſcience;</hi> yet, <hi>ſi qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem probae &amp; juſtae ſunt,</hi> if they be juſt and honeſt, we are ſo far forth obliged to obſerve them as they conduce <hi>to the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ut Eccleſiae aedificationi ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, &amp; offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculum vite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> Beza <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>edification of the Church, and that we may avoid Scandal.</hi> Thus <hi>Beza.</hi> And the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Divines do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as much in their <hi>Grand Debate,</hi> (pag. 92.) <hi>[The Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> (ſay they) <hi>are bound to obey a</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Was <hi>O. Cromwell's</hi> a true Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity? you thought your ſelves bound to obey <hi>that, true</hi> or <hi>falſe.</hi>
               </note> true <hi>Authority in ſuch impoſitions</hi> (as they are there ſpeaking of,) <hi>where the matter belongs to the Cognizance and Office of the Ruler.]</hi> But ſuppoſe I ſhould <hi>ſcruple</hi> my Obedience, <hi>thinking</hi> my <hi>Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour</hi>'s impoſitions to be againſt the commands of God. Why, even in this <hi>caſe</hi> I am obliged to <hi>lay aſide</hi> my own <hi>ſcruples,</hi> and to bring <hi>ſuch thoughts</hi> into <hi>captivity to the obedience of Chriſt,</hi> who hath commanded me <hi>to obey thoſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 13. 17.</note> 
               <hi>that have the Rule over me.</hi> My <hi>doubting</hi> whether the Command be <hi>Lawful,</hi> or whether it <hi>exceeds</hi> the Power of my <hi>Superior</hi> to command it, will not excuſe my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience. For in doubtfull matters, <hi>Melior eſt conditio Poſsidentis,</hi> He that is in <hi>poſſeſsion</hi> hath the better <hi>intereſt:</hi> And that the <hi>Superior</hi> is poſſeſt of his <hi>Right</hi> of command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is unqueſtionable; and therefore I am bound in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:95494:36"/> to ſtand for his <hi>command,</hi> till it be evinced that his command is of a thing <hi>unlawfull,</hi> or above the <hi>ſphear</hi> of his <hi>Authoritie.</hi> 'Tis true, A ſuperior cannot command a thing <hi>unlawful:</hi> but ſeeing he doth <hi>judge,</hi> upon <hi>mature</hi> delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that his command is <hi>lawful,</hi> though thou doubteſt of the Honeſty or Lawfulneſs thereof, it is much more equal, in this caſe, to ſubſcribe to his <hi>Judgment,</hi> then to give way to thy <hi>Scruple</hi> or <hi>dubitation.</hi> Otherwiſe it will unavoidably follow, that all <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> is gone, when upon the account or pretence of ſuch <hi>thinking, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> or <hi>ſcrupling,</hi> the moſt <hi>ſtubborn</hi> and <hi>pertinacious</hi> may take liberty to <hi>oppoſe</hi> all <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Orders,</hi> there being no way left to bring them to acknowledge <hi>any,</hi> as <hi>ſubſervient</hi> to the Lawes of God, or <hi>conſiſtent</hi> with them, but ſuch as <hi>Themſelves</hi> ſhall <hi>dictate</hi> or find <hi>ſuitable</hi> to their own <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have now finiſhed my deſign, and run over ſo much of <hi>The Grand Debate</hi> as I undertook to Anſwer; (The Reſt, I hope, will be managed by a better pen and judgment.) And if they have alledged any thing elſe in favour of their <hi>Pulpit-Conceptions,</hi> to the <hi>neglect</hi> or <hi>diſparagement</hi> of the <hi>Publick</hi> Form, (in ſome other Paragraphs of their <hi>Debate,</hi> which I have not yet had the leiſure to examine) I am apt to perſuade my ſelf, it is obviated in ſome part of this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>But we need no more to juſtifie the Governors of the Church in their impoſition of Set Forms, then what the evidence and force of truth hath drawn out of the very bowels of <hi>Smectymnuus</hi> to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Primò</hi> (ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">Mr <hi>Tim. Yong</hi> in his <hi>Dies Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minica,</hi> lib. 2. cap. 10. pag. 112.</note> 
               <hi>T. Y.) preces ſecundum temporis qualita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem erant adhibitae, hominum mentibus ad precandum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votè à Sp. Sancto diſpoſitis. Poſtea verò (quando aſtutiâ Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boli varii in religione obrepſerant errores) protractu tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris evenit, ut preces contra fidem ab aliquibus inveheren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:95494:36"/> 
               <hi>Proſpiciente Eccleſiâ huic Errori, triplex adhibitum erat remedium. Primò, cautum fuit, ut</hi> nulli pro arbitrio precum formulas contexere, quas in publicis conventibus recitaret, liceret, ſed <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>I. e.</hi> Such as had been uſed in the Church <hi>diuturnâ con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudine,</hi> as <hi>Zonaras</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprets it. Whence we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, that ſuch Forms had then been cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily uſed for a long time in the Church.</note> eaedem retinerentur in quocunque conventu. <hi>Ita Conc. Laod. Can.</hi> 18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deinde ſtatutum erat, ut</hi> de precibus, quibus in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſibus uterentur, cum inſtructioribus fratribus confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. <hi>Ita Conc.</hi> 3. <hi>Carthag. Can.</hi> 23. <hi>erat cautum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tandem definitum erat, ut</hi> nullae aliae preces vel oratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes dicerentur in Eccleſia, niſi quae à Synodo erant appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batae; <hi>(Concil. Milevit.</hi> 2. <hi>Can.</hi> 12.) nè forte aliquid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra fidem, vel per ignorantiam, vel per minus ſtudium, ſit compoſitum. <hi>Utriuſque remedii, ſecundi ſcilicet &amp; tertii, occurrit mentio in Concil. Afric. can.</hi> 70. T. 1. Thus he.</p>
            <p>And, not to reflect upon the Artifice which is there uſed to make theſe Authorities, if it were poſſible, to comply with the <hi>Smectymnuan</hi> deſign and intereſt, we may averre with Confidence, that never had any Church more reaſon to <hi>determine</hi> the ſeveral parts of the <hi>Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial</hi> office, then the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath at this day.</p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
